《教父2》
教父的原名是 维多安东里尼
诞生在西西里岛 的柯里昂村
1901年时 他的父亲
因侮辱当地的 黑手党老大被谋杀
他的兄长保罗发誓要复仇
却在山区里失去踪影
留下了维多在那儿
成为唯一男性
在葬礼中陪伴他的母亲
他当时才九岁
他们杀了那个孩子
They've killed the boy!
他们杀了年轻的保罗
They've killed young Paolo!
他们杀了你的儿子保罗
They've killed your son Paolo!
凶手！
Murderers! Murderers!
我的儿子！
My son…
我尊敬的西西欧阁下
All my respect, Don Ciccio.
西西欧阁下…
Don Ciccio…
你因我丈夫不肯 向你屈服而杀他
You killed my husband because he wouldn't give in to you.
以及他的长子保罗
And his oldest son Paolo…
因为他誓言要复仇
because he swore revenge.
但维多是我仅有的 而且笨手笨脚
But Vito is only nine.And dumb-witted.
他从来不说话
He never speaks.
我怕的不是他的话
It's not his words I'm afraid of.
他很弱 不可能伤害任何人
He's weak. He couldn't hurt anyone.
但他长大后会变得很强
But when he grows, he'll grow strong.
别担心 这小孩不会对你怎么样
Don't worry. This little boy can't do a thing to you.
当他长大以后会回来报仇的
When he's a man, he'll come for revenge.
我求你 西西欧阁下
I beg you, Don Ciccio, spare my only son.
放了我唯一的孩子
He's all I have left.
他是我仅有的了
我对天发誓 他永远不会伤害你
I swear to God he'll never do you any harm.
放了他吧！
Spare him!
不行
No.
快逃 维多
Run, Vito!
别动否则我杀了你！
Move and I'll kill him!
快逃！维多
Run, Vito!
杀了他！
Kill him…
任何家庭收容了维多安东里尼 都会后悔的
Any family who hides the boy Vito Andolini will regret it!
你们明白吗？
You understand?
任何收容维多安东里尼的 都会有麻烦
Anybody who hides the boy.
任何人收容了维多安东里尼…
If anyone is hiding the boy Vito Andolini…
把他交给我们
…turn him over to us.
西西欧阁下会谢谢你的 那对你及那孩子都好
Don Ciccio will thank you for it!
任何人收容了维多安东里尼…
Any family who hides the boy Vito Andolini…
维多 我们会为你祈祷的
Vito, we're praying for you!
任何收容维多安东里尼的 都会有麻烦
Anybody who hides the boy Vito Andolini is in for trouble!
把他交给我们
Turn him over to us.
西西欧阁下会谢谢你的
Don Ciccio will thank you for it!
那对你及那孩子都好
It'll be better for the boy, and better for you!
任何人收容了维多安东里尼…
Any family who hides the boy Vito Andolini…
去找护士
Nurse.
翻译员
Interpreter!
你从哪里来？
Where are you from?
你叫什么名字？
What is your name?
说吧！孩子 你叫什么名字？
Come on, son. What is your name?
你叫什么名字
What is your name?
由柯里昂村来的维多安东里尼
Vito Andolini from Corleone.
柯里昂 维多柯里昂
Corleone. Vito Corleone.
好了 到那边去
Okay, over there.
下一位
Next.
叫什么名字
Your name?
告诉他他有天花 要隔离三个月
Tell him he has smallpox. Quarantine three months.
维多柯里昂？…
Vito Corleone!Vito Corleone!
在这！他就是
Here he is. This is him.
（1901年 爱丽丝岛 维多柯里昂）
（他的孙子 安东尼维多柯里昂）
（1958年 大浩湖 内华达州）
泰德！把车钥匙拿来
Did you bring the car keys?
洛莉！
Laurie! Laurie!
妈妈！
Mama!
看看是谁在这
Look, who's here?
柯梅诺神父！
Father Carmelo.
- 这位是柯梅诺神父 - 我是梅尔强森
- This is Father Carmelo. - I'm Merle Johnson.
是这教区的神父
family parish.
妈妈！我回来了
Mama!Here I am.
我真搞不懂
Constanzia,
你来迟了一个星期？
after one week?
我上星期派车去机场接你
I sent the car to the airport last week to pick you up.
那是场大灾难
It was chaos.
反正我回来了 只是迟了一星期罢了
Anyway, here I am, just one week late.
这个是送给妈妈的
This is for my mama!
- 这是什么？- 你还记得梅尔吧？
- What is this? - You remember Merle?
你好 妈妈
Hello, mama.
你好吗？谢谢你
Hello. How are you? Thank you.
麦克在哪？我得和他谈谈
Where's Michael? I gotta to talk to him,
把几件事弄清楚
and um, get a few things straight,
我不能排队见他
and I can't wait on line.
你先去看你的孩子
You go see your children first.
然后再操心见你弟弟的事 你得和别人一样排队
Then you worry about waiting on line to see your brother. Like everybody else.
各位先生女士
Ladies and gentlemen…
我们最尊贵的来宾 想要说几句话
A most distinguished guest would like to say a few words.
请欢迎内华达州的参议员
Please welcome Senator Pat Geary.
派特葛瑞
of the State of Nevada.
还有葛瑞太太
And there is Mrs. Geary.
非常谢谢各位先生女士
Thank you very much, Ladies and Gentlemen.
对于我及内人而言 今天是个非常快乐的日子
This is a very, very happy day for me and my wife Mrs. Geary.
我们极少回来内华达州
We see Nevada far too seldom.
我们今天回来特别高兴 一来和老朋友相聚
But today we can join with old friends,
二来我们能交到新的朋友
we can make new friends,
三则是共同庆祝一个年轻人 首度领圣餐礼
and we help celebrate a young man's first Communion.
而且也要谢谢那孩子的家庭 对于本州慷慨的捐献
And also to thank that boy's family for a magnificent contribution to the State.
我手上有张支票
I have here in my hand a cheque.
受款人是州立大学
made out to the university,
而且金额惊人
and it is a magnificent endowment.
是以安东尼维多柯里昂的 名义捐赠的
in the name of Anthony Vito Corleone.
钱是安东尼父母捐出来我们有
The cheque is signed by that young man's parents,
请这对善长站起来和大家见面
whom I think we should recognise.
请站起来 让大伙们能看到你们
Mike, Pat, Kay. stand up, please. Let the folks see you!
各位 希望大家和我一起
Folks, I want you to join me.
向麦克柯里昂先生夫人致谢
in giving a real Nevada thank you to Mr. and Mrs. Michael Corleone!
我们同时有一个 特别安排的节目
We also have, as a special added attraction,
西耶华儿童合唱团
the Sierra Boys Choir,
他们特别挑选了一些歌曲
who have chosen a certain special song.
为这里的主人麦克柯里昂
and a special arrangement to.
所特别安排的
honour their host, Mr. Michael Corleone.
孩子们！
Boys.
匾额
The plaque.
对了
Relax.
好 你们拍到了没？
Okay, fellows, did you get that one?
好了 参议员 麻烦你和柯里昂太太合照
Now, Senator, just you and Mrs. Corleone.
好了 那样就行了
Okay that's enough, Senator.
请把支票给我
Give me the cheque.
拿高点让我们看得见
higher, so we can see it.
这是我的律师汤姆哈金
My lawyer Tom Hagen.
葛瑞参议员
Senator Geary.
是他负责和你的手下 安排这整件事
He arranged everything through your man Turnbull.
是的…
Yes, yes.
请坐
Sit down.
我以为我们两个要单独谈话
Well I was under the impression that you and I would talk alone.
这些人都是我的心腹 参议员
I trust these men with my life, Senator.
若是我要求他们离开 那就是侮辱他们
To ask them to leave would be an insult.
这个…
Well,
我是无所谓但是我得告诉你
it's perfectly all right with me,
我是个很直率的人
but I am a blunt man.
而我预备很坦白的对你说
and I intend to speak very frankly to you.
也许比从前任何一位 你遇过的参议员都要坦白
Maybe more frankly than anyone in my position has ever talked to you before.
柯里昂家族在内华达 相当的成功
The Corleone family has done well in Nevada.
你拥有或者说控制了 拉斯维加斯的主要旅馆
You own, or control, two major hotels in Vegas,
在雷诺还有一家
and one in Reno.
执照是早就有的
The licences were grandfathered in,
所以在赌博委员会是没有问题
so there was no problem with the Gaming Commission.
现在我的消息来源告诉我
Now my sources tell me.
你计划预备去动托比卡拉
that you plan to make a move against the Tropigala.
他们告诉我说在一周之内
They tell me that, within a week,
你就会把他们给扫地出门了
you're going to move Klingman out.
那是个不小的扩充
Quite an expansion.
不过你会遇到一个 技术上的问题
However, it will leave you with a little technical problem.
执照依然是克灵门的名字
The licence will still be in Klingman's name.
谭波是个好人
Turnbull is a good man.
好了 我们废话少说
Yeah, well, let's cut out the bullshit.
我不想在这里浪费许多时间
I don't want to spend more time here than I have to.
你可以拥有执照
You can have the licence.
代价是25万
The price is 250, 000 dollars.
加上每个月总收入的5%
Plus five per cent of the gross monthly,
柯里昂先生 我是指四家旅馆合并的总收入
of all four hotels, Mr. Corleone.
现在执照的价格不超过二万元
The price for the licence is less than 20, 000 dollars,
- 我说的对不对？- 没错
- Am I right? - That's right.
那我为何要付 这么高的价格呢？
Why would I pay more than that?
因为我意图要压迫你
Because I intend to squeeze you.
我不喜欢你这一类的人
I don't like your kind of people.
我不喜欢看到你油头粉面
I don't like to see you come out to.
穿着那纯丝的西装
this clean country in oily hair, dressed up in those silk suits.
假装是位正直的美国人
and try to pass yourselves off as decent Americans.
我是和你做生意
I'll do business with you,
但事实上我鄙视你的假面具
but the fact is that I despise your masquerade,
和你那种不择手段 向上爬的做事方式
the dishonest way you pose yourself.
你和你他妈的整个家族
Yourself, and your whole fucking family.
参议员
Senator…
我们两个都是伪善的人
…we're both part of the same hypocrisy.
但是永远也不要想 把我的家族拿来混为一谈
But never think it applies to my family.
好吧！有些人就是喜欢玩点小把戏
All right, all right.Some people have to play little games.
你玩你的
You play yours.
让我们这样说好了！
Let's say that.
你是为了自己本身的利益 而付钱给我
you'll pay me because it's in your interest.
明天中午前我要你的答覆和钱
I want your answer and the money by noon tomorrow.
还有一件事你不要再连络我了 永远不要
One more thing.Don't you contact me again, ever.
从今以后 你与罪犯去打交道
From now on you deal with Turnbull.
- 开门！小子 - 参议员
- Open that door, son. - Senator,
想的话 我现在就能答覆你
you can have my answer now if you like.
我要提供的是这个
My offer is this:
什么都没有
Nothing.
甚至不付赌博执照的费用
Not even the fee for the gaming licence.
如果你个人能提供那项费用 我会很感激的
which I would like you to put up personally.
各位午安！
Good afternoon, gentlemen.
女士们 我不知道你们在外面
Ladies! I didn't know you were out here.
亲爱的 我们必须走了 我们已经迟了30分钟了
Honey, we have to go. We're 30 minutes late.
真的 真遗憾
Really? I'm sorry.
柯里昂太太 真是个好派对 谢谢你
It's been delightful.
那是我们的荣幸 非常感谢
It was our pleasure.
和你谈话真是愉快
It was wonderful talking to you.
弗雷多
Fredo!
弗雷多 你这个臭小子
Fredo, you son-of-a-bitch,
你气色看来真好
you look great!
法兰克潘坦居利
Frank Pentangeli!
我以为你永远不会来西部你这大混蛋
I thought you was never coming out west you big bum!
我总得照顾我的手下 不是吗？
I've got to check on my boys.
弗雷多 这里的食物是怎么回事？
What's with the food here?
- 怎么了？- 穿白色上衣的孩子端给我的
- What's the matter? - A kid comes up to mein a white jacket,
几片饼干还有切碎的鹅肝 告诉我那是「可娜的和平」
gives me a Ritz cracker, and uh, chopped liver, he says Canapes.
我跟他说那是可娜和平个屁 那只是饼干配上碎鹅肝
uh, uh, can o' peas my ass, that's a Ritz cracker and chopped liver!
因为任何人都…
Hey, does anyone…
这里有烤肉 那香肠在哪里？
We got a barbecue here, so where's the sausage?
把胡椒和香肠拿出来
Bring out the peppers and sardines!
看到你让我想起了 纽约的昔日时光
Seeing you reminds me of New York in the old days!
弗雷多 你还记得威力奇契吗？
Hey, Fredo.You remember Willi Cicci.
我们和克里曼沙 一起在布鲁克林 他…
who was with old man Clemenza in Brooklyn?
我们对他的事都很难过 法兰克
We were all upset about that.
他是心脏病发作 对吧？
Heart attack, huh?
不 那不是心脏病发作
No, that was no heart attack.
那是我来这的原因
That's what I'm here.
来找你弟弟麦克谈的
to see your brother Mike about.
- 但是他是怎么回事？- 什么意思？
- But what's with him? - What do you mean?
我是说我得先去找封介绍信？
Do I have to get a letter of introduction.
才能见他？
to get a sit-down?
怎么 你不能见到麦克？
You can't get in to see Mike?
他要我在大厅等他！
He's got me waiting in a lobby!
强尼欧拉
Johnny Ola.
艾尔纳利
Al Neri.
强尼 你近来好吗？
How are you, Johnny?
你认得我的律师汤姆哈金 强尼欧拉
Do you know my lawyer Tom Hagen?Johnny Ola.
当然 老早就认得汤姆了
Sure, I remember Tom from the old days.
罗可 这是什么？
Rocco, what's this?
是迈阿密的柳丁
It's an orange from Miami.
你去招呼一下强尼的人 他们看来有点饿了
Take care of Johnny's men. They look like they might be hungry.
强尼！
Johnny!
坐吧！
Sit down!
汤姆不会在这陪我们 强尼
Tom won't stay, Johnny.
他只处理一些特别事务
He only handles specific areas of the business.
汤姆
Tom.
当然 麦克
Sure, Mike.
你要喝什么？强尼？
What are you drinking, Johnny?
蜂蜜酒
Anisette.
若需要什么？麦克 我会在外面
If you need anything, Mike, I'll be outside.
汤姆 告诉罗可我们在等他
Just tell Rocco we're waiting, Tom.
我刚留下罗斯先生在迈阿密
I just left Mr. Roth in Miami.
他的健康情况如何？
How is his health?
不好
It's not good.
我能做些什么吗？能送他什么吗
Is there anything I can do? Anything I can send?
麦克 他很感激你的关心和尊敬
We appreciate your concen Michael and your respect.
你有兴趣的那家赌场登记的是杰可劳伦斯
That casino…Registered owners: Jacob Lawrence,
和亚伦巴克莱 两个都是比佛利山的律师
Allan Barclay. Beverly Hills attorneys.
真正的主人是 克里夫兰的湖村路集团
The real owners are the old Lakeville Road group.
及我们在迈阿密的 朋友克灵门负责经营
and our friend in Miami.Meyer Klingman runs the store.
他拥有一部分的主权 他弄的还好
He runs a piece of it too, he does alright.
但是我奉命告诉你
But I've been instructed to tell you.
若你想请克灵门出局
that if you move him out,
我们在迈阿密的朋友会同意的
our friend in Miami will go along.
他们真的很客气
It's very kind of him.
你告诉他 我非常的感激
Tell him it's greatly appreciated.
海门罗斯永远为他的搭档赚钱
Hyman Roth always makes money for his partners.
一个接着一个
One by one,
昔日的好友都走了
our old friends are gone.
死了
Death.
不管是自然或其他因素
natural or not,
入狱流亡
prison, deported…
海门罗斯是唯一剩下的
Hyman Roth is the only one left,
因为他永远替他的搭档赚钱！
because he always made money for his partners.
我真不敢相信这个
I can't believe it!
有三十位职业的乐师在这
out of thirty professional musicians,
居然没有一个意大利人
there isn't one Italian in, in the group here.
来吧！我们来点意大利的乐曲 奏吧！
Let's have a tarantella! Come on!
你！站起来 快点 起来
You! Up! Clarinet up, up, up!
快点吹！
Questa mano!
吹！
混蛋 不是那个…
What the hell have we here?
我要见我姐姐一个人
I'll see my sister alone.
那和我也有关 我留下来可以吗？
It concerns me too.Is it okay, Mike, if I stay?
你好吗？亲爱的
How are you, honey?
你见过梅尔 在拉斯维加斯的时候
You've met Merle, he was with me in Vegas.
我看过他
I saw him with you.
能给我一杯酒吗？
Could I have a drink or something?
你要喝什么？
Que voi?
艾尔 请你给他杯酒好吗？
Al, would you please get him a drink!
我们下周要去欧洲
We're going to Europe next week.
我们想在皇后号上订位
I'd like to book passage on the Queen.
那你来找我干什么？
So what do you come to me for?
为何不去找旅行社呢？
Why don't you go to a travel agent?
我们先要结婚
We're getting married first.
你离婚证书上的墨水还没有干
The ink on your divorce isn't dry yet,
你就又要结婚了？
and you're getting married?
你只在周末看你的孩子
You see your children on weekends.
你知道你的长子维特 在雷诺因行窃被捕
You know your oldest boy, Victor, was picked up in Reno for some petty theft.
- 你甚至不晓得这件事 - 麦克
- that you don't even know about. - Mikey.
你和不在乎你的男人 在世界各处玩
You fly around the world with men who don't even care about you,
- 他们像对妓女一样利用你 - 你不是我父亲！
- and use you like a whore! - You're not my father!
那你来找我干什么？
Then what do you come to me for?
我需要钱！
'Cause I need money.
康妮…
Connie, Connie, Connie…
我想跟你讲道理
I wanna be reasonable with you.
你为何不留在这 和家族在一起
Why don't you stay with the family?
你能住在这 和你的孩子在一起
You can live on the estate with your kids.
你不会缺乏任何东西
You won't be deprived of anything.
你可以拥有任何你想要的东西
and you can have everything you want.
我不认识这位梅尔
I don't know this Merle.
我不知道他是干什么的 他靠什么维生
I don't know what he does or what he lives on.
你告诉他结婚是不可能的
Now why don't you tell him marriage is out of the question.
而且你不想再见到他
and you don't want to see him anymore.
他会了解的 相信我
He'll understand, believe me.
康妮
Connie.
你要是不听我的话
If you don't listen to me,
要嫁给这个男人
and marry this man…
你会令我很失望
…you'll disappoint me.
「仙丹」是什么？
What's "Chen dannay"?
「仙丹」意思是一百年！
"Cent' anni". It means 100 years.
意思是我们都将 快乐的活一百年
It means we should all live happily for 100 years.
在整个家族里！
The family.
若是父亲还活着那就是事实了
That'd be true if my father were still alive.
康妮！
Connie!
梅尔！
Merle!
见过我的嫂嫂蒂安娜！
you've met my sister-in-law Deanna.
弗雷多的太太
Fredo's wife.
- 我的荣幸 - 久仰 也是我的荣幸
- My pleasure. - How do you do.
- 他们俩很相配 - 妈妈
- They're perfect. - mama.
她说的是什么意思？
What did she mean by that?
请恕我直言
With all respect,
我不是来这吃晚饭的
I didn't come here to eat dinner!
我知道…
I know, I know.
怎么了？我只是想跳舞而已
What's the matter? I just, I just want to dance!
跳舞是一回事 你已经东倒西歪
Dancing is one thing, you're fallin' all over the floor.
我知道你是怎么回事
I know what's the matter with you.
你在吃醋 因为他才是真正的男子汉
You're just jealous because he's a real man!
别再说了 我会毒打你一顿
I swear to God, Deanna, I'm gonna belt you right in the teeth.
你连你妈妈都不敢打
You couldn't belt your mama!
你知道吗？那些意大利人
You know somethin'? These Dagos.
当他们的老婆不乖时 他们就快疯了
are crazy when it comes to their wives.
麦克说你若不能处理这件事
Michael says that if you can't take care of this,
我必须处理
I have to.
也许你去会好一点
Maybe you better.
千万别嫁给意大利人
Never marry a Wop.
他们对待你像狗屎一样
They treat their wives like shit!
我不是有意说意大利人…
I didn't mean to say Wop.
哦哦…
Ahh, Ahh woo! Rocco! Oh!
你在做什么？你这个大笨蛋 救命！弗雷多！
What are you doing to me, you big slob? Help!Fredo!
我控制不了她 麦克
I can't control her, Mikey.
你是我哥哥 弗雷多
You're my brother,
你不需要对我道歉
you don't have to apologize to me.
克里曼沙答应在他死后
Clemenza promised the Rosato brothers.
把布朗区的三块地盘 给罗萨多兄弟
three territories in the Bronx after he died.
你接管他的事业之后 并没有交给他们
You took over and didn't give it to them.
- 我不履行约定？- 你赖帐
- I weltched? - You weltched.
克里曼沙没答应他们什么
Clemenza promised them lu cazzo,
克里曼沙并没有 承诺给他们什么
Clemenza promised them nothing.
他比我还要恨那些王八蛋
He hated those son of a bitches more than I do.
法兰克 他们说你骗他们
Frankie, they feel cheated.
麦克！你高高的坐在西耶华山上
You're sitting up in the Sierra Mountains.
你喝着…他喝的是什么？
and you're drinking…What's he drinking?
香槟
Champagne.
香槟 香槟鸡尾酒
…Champagne cocktails.
而你却替我裁决
and passing judgement on.
我要如何经营我的家族
how I run my family.
你的家族依然叫柯里昂！
Your family's still called Corleone.
而且你要管理的像柯里昂家族
And you'll run it like a Corleone.
我的家族不吃这里的 也不在拉斯维加斯吃喝
My family doesn't eat here, doesn't eat in Las Vegas…
更不吃迈阿密的…
…and doesn't eat in Miami…
去他的海门罗斯
…with Hyman Roth!
法兰克 你是个老好人 我喜欢你
You're a good old man, and I like you.
多年来你一直对我父亲忠诚
You were loyal to my father for years.
罗萨多兄弟在抓人质
The Rosato brothers are taking hostages.
还有 麦克！他已经把口水吐在我脸上
They spit right in my face,
全因为迈阿密 那犹太人在支持着
all because they're backed up by that Jew in Miami.
我知道
I know.
那就是我不要你惹他们的原因
That's why I don't want them touched.
- 你不要我惹他们 - 不要！
- Not touched? - No.
我要你对他们公平点！
I want you to be fair with them.
你要我对他们公平点？
You want me to be fair with them?
天！你对禽兽如何公平？汤姆！看在老天的份上
How can you be fair to animals?
听我说 他们吸纳西班牙人
Tom, listen. They recruit spics,
他们吸纳黑人
they recruit niggers.
他们在他们祖母的 邻近地区使用暴力
They do violence in their grandmothers'neighbourhoods!
且我告诉你 他们所有的勾当 都跟妓女和贩毒有关
And everything with them is whores! And junk, dope!
他们把赌放在最后一位
And they leave the gambling to last.
我要管理我自己的家族
I want to run my family.
不需要你在背后支持
without you on my back.
- 而我要那些罗萨多兄弟的命 - 不行
- and I want those Rosato brothers dead! - No.
要！
Mort'
现在我和海门罗斯 有重要的生意要做
Now I have business that's important with Hyman Roth.
我不要被骚扰
I don't want it disturbed.
你对犹太人的忠诚 远胜过对自己的血源
Then you give your loyalty to a Jew before your own blood.
别这样 法兰克
Come on, Frankie,
你知道家父和海门罗斯 做过生意
You know my father did business with Hyman Roth.
他很尊重他们
He respected him.
令尊和海门罗斯做过生意
Your father did business with Hyman Roth,
令尊尊重海门罗斯
he respected Hyman Roth,
但他从来不信任海门罗斯
but he never trusted Hyman Roth.
或是他的西西里人信差 强尼欧拉
or his Sicilian messenger boy Johnny Ola.
对不起 我先告退了 我有点累 又有点醉了
You'll have to excuse me. I'm tired, and I'm a little drunk!
而且我要这的每一位都知道
I want everybody here to know,
我不会为各位添任何的麻烦
there's not going to be no trouble from me!
柯里昂阁下
Don Corleone.
奇契 开门
Cicci, the door…
你要他们现在离开吗？
You want him to leave now?
让他们回纽约去吧
Let him go back to New York.
我已经拟好我的计划了
I've already made my plans.
那老头酒喝的太多了
The old man had too much wine.
时候不早了
It's late.
胎儿好吗？
How's the baby?
在我体内睡着了
Sleeping inside me.
你觉得是个男孩吗？
Does it feel like a boy?
是的 是个男孩 麦克
Yes, it does, Michael.
凯
Kay?
我很抱歉今天这些人来
I'm sorry about all the people today.
时机不对 但是我也无能为力
Bad timing.It couldn't be helped, though.
它让我想到你以前告诉过我
It made me think of what you once told me.
五年内柯里昂家族事业 完全合法化
"In five years the Corleone family will be completely legitimate."
那是七年前的事了
That was seven years ago.
我知道
I know.
我在尽力 亲爱的
I'm trying, darling.
（你喜欢吗？爸爸）
你看过这个了吗？
Did you see this?
麦克 窗帘为何是开着的？
Michael, why are the drapes open?
- 凯 你还好吗？- 我还好
- Kay, are you all right? - Yeah.
- 你有没有中弹？- 没有
- Are you hit? - No.
过去了！…
It's over It's over.
把门关起来！
Get the door locked!
停住！…
Stop, stop…
他们还在这里面
They're still on the property.
拜托！麦克！拜托你留在里面
Please stay inside.
要活口
Keep them alive.
- 我们尽力 - 罗可！抓活口
- We'll try. - Alive!
留在门口
Stay by the door.
留在房子附近
Stay around house.
进来
Yeah, come in.
麦克 你还好吗？
Mike, are you all right?
很好
Yeah.
有许多事我不能告诉你
Yeah, there's a lot I can't tell you.
我知道过去你因此而很颓丧
and I now that's upset you in the past.
是有点儿
A little.
你觉得那表示缺少信任与信心
You felt it was because of some lack of trust or confidence.
但那是…
But it's…
是因为我钦佩你而且我爱你
because I admire you and love you,
所以我才对你保守秘密
that I kept things secret from you.
也因此在这个时候 你是我唯一能信任的人
Now you're the only one I can trust.
弗雷多？
Fredo?
他有个善良的心
Well, he's got a good heart.
但是他很懦弱而且很笨
But he's weak and he's stupid.
而这是生死攸关的事
nd this is life and death.
汤姆！你是我的兄弟
Tom, you're my brother.
我一直希望你把我当成你兄弟 像亲兄弟一样
I always wanted to be thought of as a brother by you, Mikey. A real brother.
我知道
I know that.
你要接管一切
You're going to take over.
你将成为族长！
You're going to be the Don.
若是发生的事和我想的一样
If what I think has happened,
我今晚就要离开这里
I'm leaving here tonight.
我给予你完全的权力
I give you complete power.
包括弗雷多及他的手下 还有罗可 纳利所有人
Over Fredo and his men. Rocco, Neri, everyone.
我把我太太的性命交付给你
I'm trusting you with the lives of my wife.
还有我的孩子
and my children,
以及这个家族的未来
the future of this family.
若是我们抓到这些傢伙
If we catch them,
你看有否可能查出 幕后主使者吗？
will we find out…
没必要去抓
We won't catch them.
除非我错的离谱
Unless I'm very wrong,
否则他们应该已经死了
they're dead already.
被一位很接近我们的人杀死
They were killed by somebody close to us.
是内奸
Inside.
非常怕会曝光
Very, very frightened that they botched it.
那么你的人呢？罗可和纳利
You don't think that Rocco and Neri.
你不会认为他们与此事有关吧
had something to do with this?
你知道吗？
See…
我们的人都是生意人
All our people are businessmen.
他们的忠诚是以那个为基础
Their loyalty is based on that.
我由爸爸那里学到了一点
One thing I learned from Pop…
试着想想你身边的人 会怎么想？
…was to try to think as people around you think.
在生意的基础上 凡事都有可能
On that basis, anything is possible.
他们死在那里 就在我窗户外面
Mike, they're dead! Right outside my window!
我要离开这里 否则死的是我
I want to get out of here.They're lying there dead!
拉她进去！
Get her in!
在这边！他们有两个人
Over here! There's two of them.
看来像是由纽约以外的人雇的
Looks like they were hired out of New York.
我不认识他们
I don't recognise them.
现在问不出什么了
Won't get anything out of them now.
看…
Look, look…
把他们解决掉
Fish them out.
好了 把尸体料理掉
Get rid of the bodies.
麦克到哪去了？
Where's Mike?
罗可！
Rocco.
安东尼！没事了 睡吧！
Anthony, everything is going to be all right. Try to sleep.
喜欢你的派对吗？
Did you like your party?
- 我收到很多礼物 - 我知道
- I got lots of presents. - I know.
你喜欢它们吗？
Did you like them?
我不认得送我礼物的那些人
Yeah. I didn't know the people who gave them to me.
他们都是朋友
Well, they were friends.
你看到我送你的礼物了吗？
Did you see my present for you?
就放在我的枕头上
It was on my pillow.
安东尼
Anthony.
我明天一大早就要离开
I'm going to be leaving very early tomorrow.
- 你会带我去吗？- 不 我不行
- Will you take me? - No, I can't, Anthony.
是什么事你必须要走？
Why do you have to go?
是生意 我必须要去
I have to do business.
我能帮你忙
I could help you.
是的 有一天你会的
I know. Some day you will.
睡一会吧！
Get some sleep.
（1917年 纽约市 维多柯里昂）
她非常美 你必须见见她
She's really beautiful.You've got to see her.
你等着看她吧 言语无法形容她的美
Wait till you see her. Words can't describe her.
我离开了那普勒斯 离开了妈妈
I left Naples. I left Mama.
为了辛苦的漂泊
For a no-good tramp!
现在我来到美国的纽约了
Now here I am in America, in New York.
独自一人 想念我的妈妈
Alone! Thinking of my mother.
没有任何家中的消息
Without news from home.
进来
Enter!
有信
Pepino, a letter for you!
你坐下
Have a seat.
终于那普勒斯来信了
Finally, a letter from Naples!
维多 喜欢我的小天使吗？
Vito, how do you like my little angel?
美吧
Isn't she beautiful?
她是很美
She's very beautiful.
对你而言 她很美
To you, she's beautiful.
而我心中只有我的妻子小孩
For me, there's only my wife and son.
亲爱的妈妈
And mama.
妈妈死了！妈妈…
Our dear mother is dead!
我们等会到后台去 带她去宵夜
We'll go backstage later and take her to eat.
你坐下 笨蛋
Sit down, you bum!
抱歉！范伦奇阁下
Oh, excuse me, Don Fanucci.
我们到后台去看她
We'll go see her backstage.
- 那是谁？- 黑手党
- Who was that? - The Black Hand.
维多 来吧！我们走
Vito, come on…
快点 我们到后台去看她
Come on let's go see her backstage.
借过！…
Sorry, sorry…
来这边
Please.
那是范伦奇 黑手党
That's Fanucci… the Black Hand.
我们明天再说吧
We'll talk about it tomorrow.
明天！永远是明天
Tomorrow! Always tomorrow!
你今天就要付钱
You'll pay me today!
我们走！
Let's go.
- 快付钱 - 别弄我女儿 放过她
- Pay me now! - Not my daughter! Let her go!
这！我所有的钱都给你
Here, take all my money!
维多…走吧
Vito, come on.
维多 我知道你怎么想
I know what you're thinking.
但事情不是那样的
But you don't know how things are.
范伦奇是黑手党
Fanucci's with the Black Hand.
这一带全都得付他钱
The whole neighborhood pays him.
即使是我开杂货店的爸爸
Even my father, in the grocery store.
他是意大利人？
If he's Italian…
他为何要骚扰 其他的意大利人？
…why does he bother other Italians?
他知道没别人保护他们
He knows they have nobody to protect them.
别管那个 喜欢我的小天使吗？
Forget that. Did you like my angel?
若是你快乐 我就快乐
If you're happy, I'm happy.
工作顺利吗
Don't you feel well?
你老板对你还好吗？
Is your boss treating you all right?
别提它了
Forget it.
隔壁的
Hey! Paisan!
你是意大利人吗？
Hey, you speak Italian?
帮我保管一下 下星期我再回来拿
Hide this for me!Next week. I'll come and get it!
阿班达多 见过我的侄子
Abbandando, meet my nephew!
生意好吗？
How's business?
很好！…
It's good, it's good.
范伦奇疯了！说邻居在拖付钱的限期
Fanucci's mad. Says the neighborhood's getting sloppy.
说人们不准时付钱 不付全额的钱
People don't pay on time, don't pay the full amount.
说他对大家都太好了
Says he's been too nice to everyone.
所以范伦奇要改变了？
So Fanucci's changing?
当然 他想收双倍的钱
Sure. He wants double from everybody.
甚至我父亲也要付双倍
Even from my father.
我是你的朋友 对不对？
I'm a friend, right?
所以你会让他在这里做事
So you'll let him work here?
维多！过来一下
Vito, come here.
我有一个坏消息
I've got some bad news.
我实在不想告诉你这个…
I feel rotten about telling you this…
但范伦奇…他有位侄子 而你必须把我的工作给他
But Fanucci… he's got a nephew…And you have to give him my job.
你从我来这起 就一直对我很好
You've always been good to me, ever since I came here.
你像父亲般照顾我
You looked after me like a father.
我谢谢你 而且我不会忘记
I thank you.And I won't forget it.
维多
Vito!
不！…
No…
不！
Oh, no!
把这个带回去
Take this to your family.
谢谢你 但是我不能接受
Thanks anyway. But please, I can't accept.
- 给你的家人 - 我不能接受
- Take this to your family. - I can't accept.
不！
No!
好漂亮的梨子
What a nice pear!
我是克里曼沙 我的货还在你那
I'm Clemenza, you still have my goods?
你是否看过里面了？
Did you look inside?
我对于不关我事的 东西没兴趣
I'm not interested in things that don't concern me.
我的一位朋友有张很好的地氈
A friend of mine has a nice rug.
也许你太太会喜欢
Maybe your wife would like it.
她当然会 但谁有钱来买呢？
Sure she would. But who has money for a rug?
那是件礼物 我晓得如何回报的
It would be a present. I know how to return a favor.
当然好 我太太会喜欢它的
Yeah, sure.My wife would like it.
跟我来
Let's go.
那王八蛋 他不在家
The son of a bitch! He isn't home!
该死！甚至连钥匙都没留下
Damn, he didn't even leave the key.
他不会介意的
Well, he won't mind.
你先请！维多！请进吧！
Come on in. Hey, Vito come on in.
别担心！进来吧！
Please come on in.
- 这是你朋友的地方？- 是的
- This is your friend's place? - Yes.
真像一座皇宫
This is a real palace.
最好的一座
One of the best.
维多！帮个忙 好吗？
Vito, give me a hand, will you?
看看那有多漂亮！尚尼
Look how pretty it is, Santino!
请进
Come on in.
没关系的 海门在里面
It's all right. Hyman's in there.
我只是在弄午餐 你要来一个鲔鱼三明治吗？
Would you like a tuna sandwich?
不 谢谢你
No, thank you.
罗斯先生？
Mr. Roth?
请进 麦克
Come in, Michael.
坐吧！像自己家一样
Sit down, make yourself comfortable.
球赛快结束了
It's almost over.
你看足球赛吗？
Do you follow the football game?
有一阵子没看了
Not for a while I haven't.
我喜欢在下午看足球赛
I enjoy watching football in the afternoon.
那是我喜爱这国家的诸事之一
One of the things I love about this country.
还有棒球
Baseball too.
我就喜欢它了 从1919年阿诺罗斯坦 成立世界联盟以来
I love bassball, ever since Arnold Rothstein fixed the World Series in 1919.
我听说你遇到了麻烦
I heard you had some trouble.
太笨了
Stupid.
拿枪做出那种行为来
People behaving like that with guns.
重要的是你安然无恙
The important thing is you're all right.
拥有健康是最重要的事！
Good health is the most important thing.
比成功金钱来的重要
More than success, more than money.
比权力更重要
More than power.
我来这是因为 将会有更多流血事件
I came here because there's going to be more bloodshed.
我要你在一切开始前先知晓
I wanted you to know.
以免引发另一场战争
so another war won't start.
没有人希望有另一场战争
Nobody wants another war.
法兰克潘坦居利到我家里来
Frank Pentangeli asked my permission.
而且他要求我的同意 除掉罗萨多兄弟
to get rid of the Rosato brothers.
当我拒绝时 他试图杀了我
When I refused he tried to have me killed.
他很笨我运气很好
He was stupid, I was lucky.
我很快的会去拜访他
I'll visit him soon.
重要的是没有任何事 会妨碍我们对于未来的计划
The important thing is that nothing interferes with ourplans for the future.
你我意见相同 没有什么比那更重要
Nothing is more important.
你是个考虑周到的年轻人
You're a wise and considerate man.
而你是位伟人 罗斯先生
And you're a great man, Mr. Roth.
我还要向你学习很多
There's much I can learn from you.
只要我能帮的上忙 麦克
Whatever I can do to help, Michael.
- 打扰了 午餐来了 - 进来
- Excuse me. Lunch. - Come in.
谢谢你 亲爱的
Thank you, my dear.
你这干什么？会震破耳膜的
You're going to break your eardrums.
- 慢慢享用吧！- 谢谢你
- Enjoy it. - Thank you.
你还年轻 我老了 又有病
You're young, I'm old and sick.
我们在往后几个月所要做的事 可以创造历史
What we'll do in the next few months will make history.
那是破天荒的事
It's never been done before.
甚至令尊作梦也想不到 会有可能做到
Not even your father would dream that such a thing could be possible.
而法兰克潘坦居利该死 你没意见吧？
Frank Pentangeli is a dead man. You don't object?
他只是个小角色！
He's small potatoes.
什么事？
What's up?
我们有客人吗？
We got company?
- 麦克柯里昂来了 - 麦克柯里昂？
- Michael Corleone is here. - Michael Corleone?
他在你的房里 你最好快点
He's in your den. You better hurry.
他等了半个小时了
He's been waiting a half hour.
有什么不对了吗？
Is something wrong?
柯里昂阁下
Don Corleone.
我希望你来之前 能先告知我一声
I wish you would have let me know you were coming.
好让我为你准备点什么
I could have prepared something.
我不想让你晓得我要来
I didn't want you to know.
你听说我家发生的事了吗？
You heard what happened?
麦克 我差点没吓死
I almost died.
- 我们后来才松了一口气 - 在我的家里
- We were so relieved. - In my home!
在我的卧室 而我太太睡在那
In my bedroom where my wife sleeps!
在我孩子玩玩具的地方
Where my children come to play.
在我的家
In my home.
我要你帮助我报复
I want you to help me take my revenge.
麦克 任何事都可以 我能做些什么？
Michael, anything. What can I do?
把和罗萨多兄弟间的 麻烦解决掉
Settle these troubles with the Rosato brothers.
麦克！我不明白！
I don't understand. I don't…
听我说 我没有你那种脑筋
I don't have your brain.
去做那些大生意
for big deals.
但这是市井之事
But this is a street thing.
那个迈阿密的海门罗斯 他在支持那些王八蛋
That Hyman Roth in Miami. He's backing up those sons-of-bitches.
我知道他在支持
I know he is.
那么是为什么？
Then why?
为何你要求我与他们谈和？麦克
So why ask me to lay down to them?
是海门罗斯叫人杀我的
It was Hyman Roth that tried to have me killed.
我知道是他
I know it was him.
老天爷！麦克
Jesus Christ, Mike.
老天爷！让我们干掉他们 去把他们全部都给做了
Jesus Christ, let's get them all.
趁我们还有力量之前 现在就去
Now while we've got the muscle.
这里以前是家父的书房
This used to be my father's old study.
现在变了
It's changed.
我还记得以前…
I remember…
在这有张大桌子
there used to be a big desk here.
当我还是孩子之时 在这附近玩耍都要很小声
I remember when I was a kid. We had to be quiet when we played near here.
我很高兴这幢房子 始终不曾落入陌生人的手里
I was very happy that this house never went to strangers.
先是克里曼沙接手 现在是你
First Clemenza took it over. Now you.
家父在这里教了我许多事情
My father taught me many things here.
就在这间房间里教我的
He taught me in this room.
他教我与朋友保持接近
He taught me, "Keep your friends close,
但是敌人要更接近
but your enemies closer."
现在若是海门罗斯看到 我出面协调这件事
If Hyman Roth sees that I interceded in this.
帮了罗萨多兄弟的忙
in the Rosato brothers' favour.
他会认为与我的关然依然良好
he'll think his relationship with me is still good.
- 明白吗？- 明白
- Capide? - Capide.
我就是要他那样想
That's what I want him to think.
我要他们完全的放松
I want him relaxed.
对我们的友谊有绝对的信心
and confident in our friendship.
那我就能查出来
Then I'll be able to find out.
我家族里的叛徒是谁？
who the traitor in my family was.
弗雷多！我是强尼
Fredo, this is Johnny Ola.
强尼欧拉！我们需要帮忙
We need some more help, Johnny.
强尼？
Johnny?
老天爷 是什么时候了？
Jesus Christ, what the hell time is it?
是谁？甜心
Who's that, honey?
听清楚 弗雷多
Listen good, Fredo,
你为何打电话到这里来？
Why are you calling me?
我不想和你谈
I don't want to talk to you.
潘坦居利和罗萨多兄弟要开会 他说他会遵守他们的协定
Pentangeli is going to accept the Rosato brothers' deal.
- 他会一个人来吗？- 我什么都不知道
- Will he come alone? - I don't know.
你们使我陷的够深了
You've got me in deep enough already.
只是一起去
Just go along,
也许协谈会很顺利
everything will be all right,
弗雷多 潘坦居利说他愿意达成协议
Fredo, Pentangeli says he's willing to make a deal.
我们只想知道他是否说真话 还是会带手下一起来
All we want to know is if he's on the level, or if he'll bring his boys.
你们对我说谎 不要再打电话给我
You lied to me. I don't want you to call me anymore.
你弟弟不会查出我们交谈过
Your brother won't find out we talked.
我不知道你在说些什么
I don't know what you're talking about.
是谁？
Who was that?
打错电话的
Wrong number.
等等 我这里没有任何人
Frankie, I've got nobody here.
在车上等 奇契
Wait in the car, Cicc'.
- 法兰克 - 没事的 奇契
- Frankie. - That's okay, Cicc'.
这是什么？
What's this?
那是我们新协议的幸运符
A lucky C note for our new deal.
路契 给我们倒杯酒
Ritchie. Give us a taste.
我们对于你的决定都很高兴 法兰克
We were all real happy about your decision, Frankie.
你不会后悔的
You won't regret it.
我不喜欢这个标识 罗萨多
I don't like the C note, Rosato.
我认为那是种侮辱
I take that as an insult.
麦克叫我向你说声好
Michael Corleone says hello!
快点 把那扇门关起来
Close the door!
前面有条子 怎么…
Your friend the cop…
路契 里面很暗
Hey, Ritch. It's dark in here.
你在营业中还是已休息？
Are you open or closed?
我只是进来整理一下
I just came in to clean up a little, you know?
什么事？
What's the matter?
地板上有东西吗？
Is that something on the floor?
不 别在这！… 安东尼 别在这！
Carmine, not here! Anthony!
你打开酒吧门 我就把你的脑袋给轰掉
You open this bar and I'll blow your head in!
弗雷多！看到你真好
Freddy, it's good to see you.
- 他怎样了？- 没事了 在后面
- How is he? - He's okay. He's in the back.
好了！女孩们！闪到一边去吧
Girls, take a hike.
在这里这间房里面
In this room here.
我要先跟他单独谈谈
I want to talk to him alone first.
别这样
Come on.
我以为我能帮助你 参议员
I thought I could help you, Senator.
哈金？
Hagen?
哈金 我没有…
Listen, I did not…
没事了
It's all right.
我什么都没有做
I didn't do anything.
好的
It's okay.
你的运气很好
You're very lucky.
我弟弟弗雷多管理这个地方
My brother Fredo operates this place.
他们最先通知他
He was called before anyone.
这若发生在别的地方
Had this happened some place else.
我们也帮不了你
we couldn't have helped you.
当我醒来时 我在地板上
When I woke up, I was on the floor.
而且我不知道那是怎么发生的
And I don't know how it happened.
你记不起来了？
You can't remember?
我昏了
I passed out.
我…我来整理！
I…I picked!
只是一场游戏
Just a game. Jesus.
老天爷
Jesus, Jesus!
主！…
Jesus God!
若是有上帝的话…
Oh God!
我不知道 而且我不了解为什么
I don't know, and I don't understand why.
我记不起来了
I can't remember.
你不需要记得 只要照我说的做
Doesn't matter, just do as I say.
打个电话到你的办公室去
Put in a call to your office.
解释一下
Explain that.
说你明天下午会到
you'll be there tomorrow.
你决定在达荷的 麦克柯里昂家里住一晚
You decided to spend the night at Michael Corleone's house in Tahoe.
我记得她在笑
I do remember that she was laughing.
我们以前也玩过
We'd done it before.
我知道我不可能伤害那个女孩
and I know that I could not have hurt that girl.
那个女孩没有家人
This girl has no family.
没有人知道她在这里工作
Nobody knows that she worked here.
等清理完毕 就不会有事了
It'll be as though she never existed.
那全是因为我们之间的友谊
All that's left is our friendship.
什么事？
Yes?
抱歉 柯里昂太太 我们奉命不能让你过去
Sorry, but we're not to let you through.
我只是要去市场
I'm just going to the market.
你只要把单子给我们 我们会为你买回来
We'll pick up anything you want.
这是谁的命令？
Whose orders are these?
哈金先生的 他正在途中
Mr. Hagen's. He's coming.
好的 那我得和哈金先生谈谈
I'll speak to him.
我本来早要跟你解释 但我在达荷市有些事要办
I wanted to explain, but I had business in Carson City.
这是顾忌你的安全 麦克的要求
It's Michael's request for your safety.
我们可以去为你买你所需要的
We'll get anything you need.
太好了 我被软禁在我的屋里
So I'm supposed to stay in my house?
不 在整座庭园中都可以活动
No, within the compound will be fine.
汤姆 我下周要带孩子们去新英格兰
We were going to New England.
取消了
That's off.
我是个囚犯 是不是？
Am I a prisoner?
我们不是那样认为 凯
That's not how we see it, Kay.
好吧！孩子们 来 我们回房去
Come on, kids. We're going back to the house.
乔！
Joe.
古巴！…
Cuba, Cuba!
各位贵宾
Most respected gentlemen.
欢迎你们光临哈瓦那市
Welcome to Havana.
我要谢谢这批著名的 美国工业家
I want to thank this distinguished group of.
继续和古巴一起合作
American industrialists for continuing to work with Cuba.
在她整个历史中
for the greatest period of prosperity.
最光荣的一段时代里
in her entire history.
威廉萧先生
Mr. William Shaw.
代表通用食品公司
representing the General Fruit Company.
康德先生和唐丹先生
Messrs Corngold and Dant.
代表美国电话电报公司
of United Telephone and Telegraph Company.
派帝先生
Mr. Petty.
是泛美矿业公司的地区副总裁
regional Vice President of the Pan American Mining Corporation.
罗勃特艾伦先生 南美糖业公司
Mr. Robert Allen of South American Sugar.
麦克柯里昂先生 来自内华达州
Mr. Michael Corleone of Nevada.
代表了我们 观光休闲活动事业的联盟
representing our associates in tourism and leisure activities.
还有我的老朋友及合伙人
And my old friend and associate from Florida.
来自佛罗里达的海门罗斯先生
Mr. Hyman Roth.
我要利用这个机会
I would like to thank.
谢谢美国电话电报公司
United Telephone and Telegraph.
所赠送的可爱的圣诞礼物
for their Christmas gift.
一座纯金的电话！
A solid gold telephone.
也许各位想要看看
Perhaps you gentlemen would like to look at it.
- 总统先生 - 什么事？
- Mr. President? - Yes?
也许你能谈谈叛乱的情况
Could you discuss the rebel activity.
这对于我们的 生意会有何影响？
and what this can mean to our businesses?
- 当然！- 好重
- Of course. - Heavy stuff.
我要向各位保证
I assure you that.
虽然叛乱分子在拉斯维拉
lthough the rebels have started.
掀起惊人的动乱
a campaign in Las Villas.
我的参谋们告诉我
my staff indicates, with assurance.
我们能在新年之前将他们 赶出圣克拉拉
that we'll drive them out of Santa Clara before the New Year.
而且我希望你们能放心
I want to put you all at ease.
我们绝不容许游击队 出现在赌场或游泳池
We will tolerate no guerrillas in the casinos or the swimming pools.
他说他们在逮捕人
He said that they're making an arrest.
几分钟后会让我们通过
and in a few minutes he'll let us through.
- 强尼 - 没什么
- Johnny. - It's nothing.
只是一群盗匪 警察在肃清他们
Just some lousy bandits.The police are cleaning them up.
你的蛋糕来了
Viva Fidel!
希望我的年龄没弄错
I hope my age is correct.
我对我的年龄一向很确定
I'm always accurate about my age.
在切蛋糕之前 让大家都看看蛋糕
Make sure that everybody sees the cake before we cut it.
我非常的高兴
I'm very pleased.
你们从各地方前来 与我在这里相聚
you're all able to come from such distances to be with me today.
当一个人到了 他生命中的这一刻
When a man comes to this point in his life.
他希望能将他被祝福的事 交付出去
he wants to turn over the things he's been blessed with.
把它们交给朋友
Turn them over to friends.
像是给他所有的 朋友一种补偿
as a reward for the friends he's had.
也是要确定在他死了之后
And to make sure that.
一切事情都还能够顺利进行
everything goes well after he's gone.
那还得等上很多年
Not for years.
我们会知道的 医生们不同意
We'll see. The doctors would disagree.
但他们又晓得什么？
but what do they know?
我们在哈瓦那 所达成的美好成就
These are wonderful things that we've achieved in Havana.
由此开始毫无止境
and there's no limit to where we can go from here.
这种政府了解如何协助企业 如何去鼓励…
This kind of government knows how to help business, to encourage it.
这里的旅馆事业 和我们在拉斯维加斯
The hotels here are bigger and swankier than.
任何粗鄙的场所 都要更大 更豪华
any of the joints in Vegas.
我们要谢谢在古巴政府的友人
We can thank our friends in the Cuban government.
在平等的基础上 放宽了进口的限制
which has put up half the cash with the Teamsters, on a dollar for dollar basis.
而且只需先付一半的现金
and has relaxed restrictions on imports.
我要说的是
What I'm saying is.
我们有了我们所需要的
that we have now what we have always needed:
与政府的真正合伙关系
Real partnership with a government.
小块一点
Smaller piece.
你们全都认得麦克柯里昂
You all know Michael Corleone.
而且我们全都记得他的父亲
and we all remember his father.
在我退休或死亡的时候
At the time of my retirement, or death.
我把我整个哈瓦那所有的企业
I turn over all my interests in the Havana operation.
全移转给他管理
to his control.
但是…
But.
你们全部都会有一份
all of you will share.
纳西翁雷归湖村路兄弟管理
The Nacionale will go to the Lakeville Road Boys.
卡普利归柯里昂家族
the Capri to the Corleone family.
塞维拉毕特摩也是
the Sevilla Biltmore also.
但新港的艾迪拉文 将引进潘尼诺兄弟
but Eddie Levine will bring in the Pennino brothers.
尼诺和艾迪得一部分的主权
Dino and Eddie, for a piece.
和实际赌场经营的管理权
and to handle the casino operations.
而且还保留一部分 给内华达的朋友
We've saved a piece for some friends in Nevada.
以确定家乡的事都能够顺利
to make sure that things go smoothly back home.
希望大家好好享用蛋糕
I want all of you to enjoy your cake.
所以…吃吧！
So, enjoy!
生日快乐
Happy birthday!
我今天看到一件有趣的事
I saw an interesting thing happen today.
一个叛党被宪兵逮捕了
A rebel was being arrested by the military police.
他不但不肯被生擒 还引爆身上的手榴弹
Rather than be taken alive, he exploded a grenade he had in his jacket.
他自杀了 还连带炸死一位指挥的队长
He killed himself and took a captain of the command with him.
- 对吧？强尼 - 那些叛党 他们是神经病
- Right, Johnny? - Those rebels are lunatics.
也许如此 不过这使我想到 军人是拿薪水作战
Maybe so.But it occurred to me, that the soldiers are paidto fight.
叛党则不是
the rebels aren't.
那告诉了你什么？
What does that tell you?
他们可能会赢！
They can win.
这国家过去50年来都有叛乱
This country has had rebels for 50 years.
他们的天性就是如此 相信我 我知道
It's in their blood.I know.
我由20年代就开始来这里了
I've been coming here since the Twenties.
当你还是婴儿时
We were running molasses from Havana.
我们就在这经营哈瓦那的糖业
when you were a baby.
那卡车是令尊所有的
The trucks were owned by your father.
麦克
Mikey.
我宁愿我们单独相处时 才讨论这事
I'd rather we talked about this when we're alone.
那二百万一直没来到岛上
The two million never got to the island.
我不希望话传出去说 你因担心叛乱…
It mustn't be known that you held back the money.
而不肯把钱拿出来
because you worried about the rebels.
坐下…
Sit down, Michael. Sit down.
我若能活到看见 和你一起达到顶峰就好了
If I could only live to see it, to be there with you.
我愿用一切来换取20年的寿命
What I wouldn't give for 20 more years.
我们在这里被保护着
Here we are, protected.
能自由的争取我们的利润
Free to make our profits without Kefauver.
而不被司法部及调查局打扰
the goddamn Justice Department and the FBI.
身在90英里之外
90 miles away.
与友善的政府合伙
in partnership with a friendly government.
也许有些小事情 但不算什么
90 miles. It's nothing.
对一个想成为美国总统的人
Just one small step for a man looking to.
这只是小小的一步罢了
be President of the United States.
又有足够的金钱让它成为可能
and having the cash to make it possible.
麦克！
Mikey!
我们比美国钢铁公司还要大
we're bigger than U.S. Steel.
麦克！你好吗？
Mikey, how are you? Okay?
我是弗雷多柯里昂
Hi! Freddie Corleone.
是我哥哥
Mio frati.
老天爷！这一路真辛苦
Jesus Christ, what a trip!
一路上我都在想万一有人知道
I thought, "What if somebody knows.
我这里面装了什么
what I've got in here".
你能想像吗？
Can you imagine that?
二百万元在飞机座位旁
Two million dollars on the seat next to me.
- 对不起 - 没关系的
- Excuse me. - It's okay.
你要数数看吗？
You want to count it?
麦克 这里究竟是怎么回事
What's going on?
我完全蒙在鼓里
I'm totally in the dark.
家族在哈瓦那要进行投资
The family is making an investment in Havana.
这些是给总统的礼物
This is a gift for the President.
那太好了 哈瓦那好极了
That's great! Havana's great.
是我这种人的城市
It's my kind of town.
有我认识的人在哈瓦那吗？
Anybody I know in Havana?
我不知道 有海门罗斯 强尼欧拉
Don't know. Hyman Roth, Johnny Ola?
不认得 我从未见过他们
No. I've never met them.
听我说 麦克 我…
Listen, Mikey, I'm kind of…
我有点…
…kind of.
这一路上让我有点紧张
nervous from the trip.
我能…喝杯酒吗？
Can I get a drink or something?
我想也许我们可以一起出去
I thought maybe we'd go out together.
我知道一个好地方 好不好？
I know a place where we can spend some time together.
有时候我想我应该娶 像你老婆一样的女人
Sometimes I think I should have married a woman like you did.
像凯 有孩子 能和他们一起玩耍
Like Kay.Have kids. Have a family.
在我生命中能有一次
For once in my life.
我能够像爸爸那样
be more like Pop…
当个儿子并不容易 弗雷多
It's not easy to be a son, Fredo.
不容易的
It's not easy.
妈以前常取笑我说 「你不是我生的」
Mama used to say, "You don't belong to me."
你是吉普赛人留在门口的 有时候我认为那是真的
"You were left on the doorstep by gypsies."Sometimes I think it's true.
你不是吉普赛人留下的
You're no gypsy, Fredo.
麦克 我…
Mikey… I…
我以前生你的气
I was mad at you.
为何从前我们不曾 像这样一起共聚
Why didn't we spend time like this before?
你要喝一杯 对吧？
You want a drink, right?
侍者
Waiter!
香蕉大克利酒怎么讲？
How do you say Banana Daquiri?
就是香蕉大克利
Banana Daquiri.
- 就那样？- 就那样！
- That's it? - That's it.
来一杯香蕉大克利酒
Uno Banana Daquiri.
香蕉大克利酒
Banana Daquiri.
还有一杯苏打汽水
and a club soda.
葛瑞参议员明晚由华府飞来
Senator Geary flies in from Washington tomorrow.
还有一些人 一些政府要员
with some government people.
我要你让他们 在哈瓦那好好玩玩
I want you to show them a good time in Havana.
我的专长！对吧？
That's my speciality, right?
我能在某些事上信任你吗？弗雷多
Can I trust you with something?
当然！麦克
Of course, Mike.
晚上我们将应邀至总统府 参加除夕晚会
Later in the evening we're all invited to the President to bring in the New Year.
结束之后 他们会用军车载我回家
After it's over they'll take me home in a military car.
只有我一个人 为了保护我的安全
alone.For my protection.
在我到达旅馆之前 我会被刺杀
Before I reach my hotel, I'll be assassinated.
- 是谁？- 罗斯！
- Who? - Roth.
是罗斯想在家里杀我
It was Roth who tried to kill me in my home.
一直都是罗斯
It was Roth all along.
他表现的好像我是他的儿子
He acts like I'm his son.
他的接班人
his successor.
但他认为他能长生不死
But he thinks he'll live forever.
他要除掉我！
and wants me out.
我能怎么帮忙？
How can I help?
你只须装作什么都不知道 我已经做了安排
Just go along, as if you know nothing.I've already made my move.
什么安排？
What move?
海门罗斯永远见不到这个新年
Hyman Roth won't see the New Year.
他说你要放轻松点 他会开处方
Says you have to take it easy.And he's gonna give you a prescription.
- 他明天会再来 - 我要我自己的医生
- He'll be back tomorrow. - I want my own doctor.
让他从迈阿密飞过来
Fly in my own doctor from Miami.
别信任不会说英文的医生
I don't trust a doctor who can't speak English.
- 谢谢你 先生 - 不必客气
- Gracias, senor - Buenas noches.
亲爱的 到下面赌场去玩
Honey, go to the casino.
假如你确定你感觉好多了
If you're feeling better.
我会没事的
Feel fine.
去玩宾果游戏吧！
Play the bingo game.
- 幸会 柯里昂先生 请自便 - 谢谢
- Okay. Nice to see you, Mr. Paul. Just make yourself home. - Thank you.
我的第六感告诉我 你哥哥弗雷多
My sixth sense tells me Fredo.
带来了一大袋钱
brought a bag full of money.
在哪里？
Where is it?
你要退出？
You're pulling out?
只是想要…
Just want to…
只是想要等一等
Just want to wait.
- 你感觉如何？- 糟透了
- How do you feel? - Terrible.
只要小便时不会痛
I'd give four million to be able.
我愿意付四百万美金
to take a painless piss.
谁杀了法兰克潘坦居利？
Who had Frank Pentangeli killed?
是罗萨多兄弟
The Rosato brothers.
我知道 但是谁准他们动手的
I know, but who gave the go-ahead?
我知道不是我
I know I didn't.
有个从小和我一起长大的孩子
There was this kid I grew up with.
比我年轻
He was younger than me.
他蛮尊敬我的
Sort of looked up to me.
我们…
you know.
一起做了我们的第一件工作
We did our first work together.
在街头打下了一片江山
Worked our way out of the street.
事情很顺利 我们也赚了很多钱
Things were good.
在禁酒时期 我们把蜜糖 运到加拿大发了笔大财
During Prohibition we ran molasses into Canada.Made a fortune.
令尊也是
Your father too.
如同其他人一样 我爱他
As much as anyone, I loved him and.
而且信任他
trusted him.
不久之后 他有个主意
Later on he had an idea.
在沙漠建了一座城市
to build a city.
给要去西岸的军人休息之用
out of a desert stop-over for G.I.s going to the West Coast.
那孩子的名字是莫格林
That kid's name was Moe Greene.
他所创建的城市是拉斯维加斯
and the city he invented was Las Vegas.
他是个了不起的人
This was a great man.
一个有眼光 有胆量的人
A man of vision and guts.
而在那城市中 没有任何纪念他的徽章或路标
And there isn't even a plaque, signpost.
或是他的铜像
or statue of him in that town.
原因是有人用子弹 穿过他的眉心
Someone put a bullet through his eye.
没有人晓得是谁下的命令
No one knows who gave the order.
当我听到他的死讯时 我没有生气
When I heard it, I wasn't angry.
我了解莫 我知道他脾气火爆
I knew Moe, I knew he was headstrong.
说话大声 会得罪人
Talking loud, saying stupid things.
所以他死了
So when he turned up dead.
我也不去追究
I let it go.
我对我自己说
And I said to myself.
这是我们自己选择的行业
This is the business we've chosen.
我没有问
I didn't ask.
是谁下的令
who gave the order.
因为那和生意一点关系也没有
because it had nothing to do with business.
在你房间里的二百万
That two million in a bag in your room.
我要进去睡一会儿
I'm going in to take a nap.
当我醒来时
When I wake.
若是钱在桌子上
if the money is on the table.
那我就有个合伙人了
I know I have a partner.
若不在 我就知道我没有了
If it isn't, I know I don't.
好了 在座的是否都认识？
Does everybody know everybody?
这位是葛瑞参议员 你认识他
This is senator Geary, you know him.
- 你好吗？先生 - 幸会 麦克
- How are you, senator? - Good to see you, Mike.
很高兴能在这里共聚
I'm glad we spend this time together.
麦克！这位是佛州的派顿参议员
Senator Payton from Florida.
你好吗？麦克
How ya doin', Mike?
纽约的迪马克法官
Judge DeMalco from New York.
- 你好吗？先生 - 很好！谢谢
- How do you do, Sir? - Fine, thank you.
这位是马里兰州的瑞恩参议员
Senator Ream from Maryland.
麦克 我一直期待与你见面
Mike, I've been looking forward to it.
美国电话电报公司的康德先生
Fred Corngold from UTT.
我认得康德 你好
I know Fred, how are you?
他的恰恰跳得很棒 待会可要留神
That Freddie does a mean Cha Cha Cha so watch out later.
他是吗？
Oh he does, huh?
好了 各位！是「加油时间」了
Okay, gentlemen, it's refill time here.
你们也许该试试本地的酒类
You might try some of those local drinks,
知道吗？像是「古巴自由」
you know "Cuba Libra"
「克拉达先生」之类的
"Pi?a Colada"
我想要试试那…黑头发的妞
I think I'll try one of those red headed Yolandas.
那没问题！你有了！
That you got! Con gusto…
强尼
Johnny!
你不认识家兄弗雷多 对不对？
You don't know my brother Fredo.
强尼欧拉 弗雷多
Johnny Ola, Fredo.
我们从未见过 我是强尼欧拉 幸会
We never met. Johnny Ola. Pleasure.
各位！敬在哈瓦那的一夜
Gentlemen, to a night in Havana!
- 新年快乐！- 新年快乐！
- Happy New Year! - Happy New Year!
- 新年快乐 - 没错
- Feliz Ano Nuevo! - Happy New Year.
在那里 就在那里 别怕
It's there, it's there. Don't afraid.
弗雷多！我们干嘛站着？
Hey, Freddie, why are we standing?
每个人都站着
Everybody stands.
但这值得的 你看 你不会相信这个的
It's worth it. You won't believe this.
我已经开始不相信
I don't believe it already.
赌50元 对吧？
50 dollars, right?
赌了！参议员
You've got a bet, mister.
就是他！那就是超人！
That's Superman.
我说了吧？我说过了吧？
Did I tell you or did I tell you?
我不相信
I don't believe it!
那东西一定是假的
It's got to be fake.
不是假的 那是真的 所以才叫他超人
It's real. That's why he's called Superman.
弗雷多！…
Hey, Freddy.
你怎么找到这地方的？
where did you find this place?
强尼欧拉告诉我这地方
Johnny Ola brought me here.
他带我来这的 我并不相信他
I didn't believe it.
但眼见为凭 对吧？
but seeing is believing!
我看到了但依然不相信
I see it, but still don't believe it!
派顿 50块钱
50 bucks, Pat.
罗斯老头从来不到这里来
Roth won't go here.
但强尼对这地方是瞭如指掌
but Johnny knows these places like the back of his hand.!
注意看！他要把那打碎了
Now watch him, he's gonna break a cracked with it.
打碎那个？我要看他打断一座桥
Break a cracker? I want to see him break a brick.
他可以打到月亮上！
He could knock down a building.
放轻松点！罗斯先生
Relax!Se?or Roth.
我们立刻送你到医院去
we're taking you to the hospital.
依我的判断你能继续你的目标
And in my judgment, you'll continue to get those,
因为我不相信
because I don't believe.
艾森豪总统会撤出古巴
that President Eisenhower well ever pull out of Cuba.
只要我们在古巴 有超过十亿美金的投资
not as long as we have over one billion dollars.
他就不会撤走
invested in this country.
美国相信不干涉政策…
The American public believe in non-intervention…
弗雷多！
Fredo!
你去哪？
Where are you going?
我要去倒杯真正的酒
I'm getting a real drink.
因为这个会要了我的命
because I can't…
罗斯先生怎么还不来？
What kept Mr. Roth?
我知道他要来的
I understood he was coming.
外交礼节是怎么样？
Reeves, what's the protocol?
我们要在这停留多久？
How long should we stay?
我不知道
I don't konw.
我想半个小时就可以了
I think a half hour ought to do it.
只要等到新年来临即可
Just long enough to bring in the New Year.
是除夕夜 来吧！一分钟就好
It's New Year's Eve. Come on, just for a minute.
有架飞机在等我们
There's a plane waiting.
一小时内带我们到迈阿密 知道吗？
to take us to Miami in an hour.
不要把它看得太严重
Don't make a big thing about it.
我知道是你！弗雷多
I know it was you, Fredo.
你伤了我的心！
You broke my heart.
You broke my heart!
鉴于我们的部队在关达那摩 及圣地牙哥严重的挫败
Due to serious setbacks to our troops in Guantanamo and Santiago.
我在古巴的地位已经动摇
my position in Cuba is untenable.
为避免更多的流血战争 我将辞去总统职位
I am resigning from office to avoid further bloodshed.
而且我会立刻离开这座城市
And I shall leave the city immediately.
我祝你们好运！
I wish all of you good luck.
弗雷多！来吧！跟我一起走！
Fredo!Come on. Come with me.
这是今晚离开这的唯一方法！
It's the only way out of here tonight.
罗斯已经死了！弗雷多
Roth is dead!Fredo.
弗雷多！跟我一起走！
Fredo, come with me!
你仍然是我哥哥！弗雷多…
You're still my brother.Fredo…
只有美国公民才行！
Passports, Passports, U.S. passports only, please.
让我们过去！我是美国参议员
Pass through, I'm Pat GEARY of the United States Senate!
- 请退后！- 拜托 等一下 拜托
- Get back! - Please, I must leave!
艾尔！给我一条湿毛巾
Al. Get me a wet towel.
凯知道我回来吗？
Does Kay know I'm back?
我的孩子呢？圣诞节有送东西给他们吗？
My boy? Did you get him something for Christmas?
我料理了
I took care of it.
送的是什么东西？
What was it, so I'll know.
是辆有电动马达的小车 他能驾驶
It was a little car with an electric motor that he can ride in.
还不错
It's nice.
谢谢 艾尔
Thank you, Al.
艾尔 你们是否能出去一会儿？
Fellows, could you step outside for a minute?
我哥哥呢？
Where's my brother?
罗斯坐私人船回来了
Roth got out on a private boat.
在迈阿密医院
He's in a hospital in Miami.
心脏病发作过一次 但复元情况良好
He had a stroke, but recovered okay.
你的侍卫死了
Your bodyguard is dead.
我在问弗雷多的事
I asked about Fredo.
我想他逃出来了 一定在纽约某处
I think he got out. He must be somewhere in New York.
好吧！
All right.
我要你和他连络
I want you to get in touch with him.
我晓得他害怕
I know he's scared.
但告诉他一切都没事了
Tell him everything is all right.
我知道是罗斯唆使他的
Tell him I know Roth misled him.
他并不知道他们想杀我
That he didn't know they would try to kill me.
叫他们进来吧！
They can come in now.
麦克 还有别的事
There was something else.
什么事？
What?
说吧！什么事？快说
What? Come on.
凯小产了！孩子没保住！
Kay had a miscarriage.
是个男孩吗？
Was it a boy?
麦克 才三个半月大
At three and a half months.
你不能直接了当给我答案吗？
Can't you give me a straight answer?!
是个男孩吗？
Was it a boy?
我真的不知道
I really don't know.
可怜的小弗雷多 他得了肺炎
Poor little Fredo, he's got pneumonia.
年轻人 我听说你 及你的朋友们在偷东西
Young man, I hear you and your friends are stealing goods.
但你们连套衣服 也没送到我家去
But you don't even send a dress to my house.
不尊重我
No respect!
你知道我有三个女儿
You know I've got three daughters.
这是我的地盘
This is my neighborhood.
你与你的朋友们 应该对我尊敬些
You and your friends should show me some respect.
你应该分我一份
You should let me wet my beak a little.
我听说你与你的朋友们
I hear you and your friends.
每人分得了六百元
cleared $600 each.
为了你们的安全 每人给我二百元保护费
Give me $200 each, for your own protection.
那我就忘了这侮辱
And I'll forget the insult.
你们年轻的混蛋该学习
You young punks have to learn.
尊重像我这一类的人
to respect a man like me!
否则条子会到你们家去
Otherwise the cops will come to your house.
那你们的家就被毁了
And your family will be ruined.
当然 若是我弄错了 你们行窃的金额
Of course if I'm wrong about how much you stole.
我可以少收一点 每人少收一百元
I'll take a little less.And by less, I only mean a hundred bucks less.
别拒绝我 了解吗？
Now don't refuse me.
- 了解吗？同乡 - 我了解
- Understand, paesano? - I understand.
我与我的朋友们把钱全分了
My friends and I share all the money.
所以我得先和他们谈
So first, I have to talk to them.
去和你的朋友们谈谈
Tell your friends.
我要的不多 分一份而已
I don't want a lot. Just enough to wet my beak.
别怕告诉他们
Don't be afraid to tell them!
六百元
600 bucks.
若是我们不付呢？
Suppose we don't pay?
你知道他们那帮人 泰西欧
You know his gang, Tessio.
真正的野兽！
Real animals.
马朗萨拉让范伦奇在这一带混
Maranzalla himself let Fanucci work this neighborhood.
而且他与条子有来往！
He's got connections with the cops, too.
我们必须付给他
We have to pay him.
每人二百元 大家同意吗？
$200 each…everybody agreed?
我们干嘛得付给他？
Why do we have to pay him?
维多 这件事交给我们
Vito, leave this to us.
他只有一个人 我们有三个
He's one person, we're three.
他有枪 我们也有枪
He's got guns, we've got guns.
为何要将我们的血汗钱送给他
Why should we give him the money we sweated for?
这里是他的地盘
This is his neighborhood!
我认识两个不付钱给范伦奇的
I know two bookies who don't give anything to Fanucci.
他们不付钱给范伦奇
They don't pay Fanucci.
若他们不付钱给范伦奇
If they don't pay Fanucci.
就是另外有人为马朗萨拉去收
then somebody else collects for Maranzalla!
我们若付他钱 他就不会再缠我们了
We'll all be better off if we pay him.
别担心
Don't worry.
我现在说的仅止于这个房间
Now what I say stays in this room.
若是你们俩愿意
If you both like.
为何不每人给我50元付范伦奇
why not give me $50 each to pay Fanucci?
我保证他会接受我付给他的
I guarantee he'll accept what I give him.
若是范伦奇说二百元
If Fanucci says $200.
他就是要那么多 维多
he means it, Vito!
我会和他讲道理
I'll reason with him.
把事情交给我吧！
Leave everything to me.
我会料理一切的
I'll take care of everything.
我从不对我的朋友说谎
I never lie to my friends.
明天你们俩都去和范伦奇谈
Tomorrow you both go talk to Fanucci.
他会要那笔钱
He'll ask for the money.
告诉他你们会如数奉上
Tell him you'll pay whatever he wants.
别和他争论
Don't argue with him.
然后我会去让他同意
Then I'll go and get him to agree.
既然他那么强硬 别和他争论
Don't argue with him, since he's so tough.
你怎么可能让他少拿点？
How can you get him to take less?
那是我的事
That's my business.
只要记得我帮了你们一个忙
Just remember that I did you a favor.
- 一言为定？- 好
- Is it a deal? - Si.
干杯！
Salute.
他的家人出去了
His family's out of the house.
范伦奇一个人在咖啡厅里
Fanucci's alone in the cafe.
维多 这是我的50元
Vito, here's my 50 dollars.
维多！你确定他会收吗？
Buona fortuna, are you sure he's going to go for it?
我会让范伦奇不能拒绝
I'll make an offer he don't refuse.
别担心
Don't worry.
看起来我帽子下有一百元
It looks like there's $100 under my hat.
我说对了 只有一百元
I was right.Only $100…
我目前缺钱用
I'm short of money right now.
我失业了 给我一点时间
I've been out of work, so just give me a little time.
你了解的 对吧？
You understand, don't you?
你有胆量年轻人
You've got balls, young man!
我以前为何没听到你的名字？
How come I never heard of you before?
你非常有胆量
You've got a lot of guts.
我会帮你找份赚大钱的工作
I'll find you some work for good money.
不伤感情 对吧？
No hard feelings, right?
若我能帮你 让我晓得
If I can help you, let me know.
祝你佳节愉快
Enjoy the festa!
范伦奇阁下
Don FANUCCI.
好极了…
Forzzelando!
这对我来说太暴力了
Oh, this is too violent for me!
你在这里干什么？
What've you got there?
麦克 爸爸非常的爱你
Michael, your father loves you very much.
奇契先生 从1942年到现在
Mr. Cicci, from the year 1942 to the present time,
你是杰安可橄榄油公司的职员
you were an employee of the Genco Olive Oil Company?
没错
That's right.
但事实上
But in actuality.
你是柯里昂犯罪组织的成员
you were a member of the Corleone crime organisation.
不 我们叫做柯里昂家族
No, we called it the Corleone family,
参议员 我们称之为家族
Senator.we called it the family.
你的职务是什么？
What was your position?
起初跟其他人一样 只是个打手
At first, like everybody else, I was a soldier.
那是什么？
What is that?
一颗枪子儿 你知道是什么 参议员
A button, you know, Senator.
不 我不知道 告诉我
No, I don't know. Tell me.
当老板说给某人一颗枪子儿时
When the boss says "push a button" on a guy,
我就给他一颗枪子儿
I push a button.
明白吗？参议员
See, Senator?
奎斯特先生
Mr. Questadt.
- 你是说你杀人 - 我什么？
- You mean you kill people? - I what?
你服从上级的命令去杀人
You kill people at the behest of your superiors.
没错！大律师！
Yeah, that's right.
而你们家族的 老大是麦克柯里昂
And the head of your family is Michael Corleone?
是 大律师 麦克柯里昂 对了
Yeah, Counsellor. Michael Corleone.
你是否有直接收到
Did you ever get such an order.
麦克柯里昂下的命令？
directly from Michael Corleone?
没有 我从来没和他说过话
No, I never talked to him.
奇契先生
Mr. Cicci.
你是否能详细说明你的答案？
Could you amplify your answer a bit?
要我做什么？
Do what?
你是否能回答得更详细
Could you expand on your answer?
尤其是是否你跟上级之间 永远有中间人
I'm particularly interested in knowing, was there always a buffer involved?
在你和发出实际命令的 上级间的中间人
Someone in between you and your superiors who gave the order.
是 对的 中间人
Right, a buffer.
家族中有许多的中间人
The family had a lot of buffers!
奇契先生 你也许觉得这很好玩
You may find this very amusing,
但我告诉你 委员会的成员不这么想
but the members of this committee do not.
告诉我 妈 在父亲内心深处 他想些什么？
Tell me something, Ma.What did Papa think deep in his heart?
他以前很坚强
He was being strong.
为他的家庭而坚强
Strong for his family.
可是为他的家坚强以外
But by being strong for his family.
他会不会失去它？
could he lose it?
你在想你太太及失去的孩子
You're thinking about your wife about the baby you lost.
但你与你太太都还能再生孩子
But you and your wife can always have another baby.
不 我是说…失去他的家
No, I meant… lose his family,
但你永远不会失去你的家
But you can never lose your family.
时代变了！
Times are changing.
不 是我的荣幸 不要钱
It's my pleasure. I don't want money.
- 把它当礼物吧！- 谢谢 非常谢谢
- Take it as a gift. - Thanks.
如果有什么我可以帮忙的 你来 我们谈谈
If there's something I can do for you, you come, we talk.
谢谢…
Grazie.
柯伦波太太 你找我有什么事？
Signora Colombo, why did you come to see me?
你太太叫我来问你是否能帮我
Your wife told me to ask if you could help me.
她有大麻烦
She's in bad trouble.
他的邻居向房东抱怨她的狗
Her neighbors complained to the landlord about her dog.
他叫她把动物丢掉
He told her to get rid of the animal.
但她的小儿子爱那条狗
But her little boy loves that dog.
所以她留下了它
So she hid it.
但当房东发现之后
When the landlord found out.
他很生气 叫她搬走
he got mad and told her to leave.
现在即使她把狗送走 也无法住下去了
Now she can't stay even if she gets rid of it.
我好惭愧
I'm so ashamed!
他说要叫警察把我们扔到街上
He said he'd get the police to throw us out on the street.
我很抱歉 但…
I'm sorry, but…
我能给你一些钱帮你搬家
I could give you a couple dollars to help you move.
我不能搬
I can't move!
我要你和他谈谈
I want you to talk to him!
告诉他我希望住在这里
Tell him I want to stay here!
你的房东叫什么名字？
What's your landlord's name?
他是罗勃特先生
His name is Signor Roberto.
他住在第四街 离这很近
He lives on Fourth Street, near here.
他们打破窗户 弄脏地板
They break the windows, they dirty the floors…
真是猪 对吧？
A real pig-sty, eh?
罗勃特先生
Mr.Roberto.
我是维多柯里昂
My name is Vito Corleone.
柯伦波太太是内人的朋友
Signora Colombo is a friend of my wife.
她说没有正当理由 就要赶她搬家
She says she's been evicted for no good reason.
她是个穷寡妇 没人照料她
She's a poor widow, she has nobody to take care of her.
她没有亲人 没有钱
She has no relatives, no money.
她所有的只是这一带的邻居
All she has is this neighborhood.
我已经把那地方租给别人家了
I already rented the place to another family.
我告诉过她我会和你谈谈
I told her that I'd talk to you.
而你是个讲道理的人
That you're a reasonable man.
她已经弄走惹麻烦的狗了
She got rid of the animal that caused all the trouble.
让她留下来吧！
So let her stay.
- 你是不是西西里人？- 不 我是卡拉布列兹人
- Are you Sicilian? - No, I'm Calabrese.
我们实际上是同乡 帮我一个忙
We're practically paesani, do me this favor.
我已经租出去了 反悔的话 我会看起来像个白痴
I already rented it! I'll look like an idiot.
而且新房客的房租要高一些
Besides, the new tenants pay more rent.
一个月多少钱？
How much more a month?
五块钱
Five bucks.
这里是先付六个月的涨价租金
Here's six months increase in advance.
但别告诉她 她的自尊心很强
But don't tell her about it. She's very proud.
六个月到了再来找我
Come see me in another six months.
当然 那条狗留下 对吧？
Of course, the dog stays. Right?
那条狗留下
The dog stays.
你算什么？来对我下命令？
Who the hell are you to come give me orders?
小心我把你那 西西里屁股踢上街
Watch out or I'll kick your Sicilian ass right into the street!
帮我一个忙 我不会忘记的
Do me this favor.I won't forget it.
向你这一带的朋友打听我
Ask your friends in the neighborhood about me.
他们会告诉你 我会回报的
They'll tell you I know how to return a favor.
好一个厉害的傢伙
What a character!
维多 那个叫罗勃特的房东来了
That landlord is here… Roberto.
专门出租房子那个
the one who owns those ratholes.
他在这一带一直打听你
He's been asking all around the neighborhood about you.
谢谢
Grazie.
希望我没打扰你 维多阁下
I hope I'm not disturbing you, Don Vito.
有何效劳之处？罗勃阁下
What can I do for you, Don Roberto?
真是场误会！圣母玛丽亚
What a misunderstanding! Holy Mary!
柯伦波太太当然能留下来
Of course Signora Colombo can stay!
谢谢！…
Grazie…
维多阁下 我要把你给我的钱还你
I'm giving back the money you gave me.
一 二 三 四 五 六 全都在这
Un, due, three, four, five, six, tutt'!
维多阁下 毕竟钱非一切
Because after all, Don Vito, money isn't everything.
我能坐下吗？
Can I sit down?
谢谢
Grazie.
你对寡妇的仁慈令我自己惭愧
Your kindness to that widow made me ashamed of myself.
房租和以前一样
The rent stays like before!
而且…我会降价
I'll even lower it.
我减五元
I'll lower it $5.
我减十元
I'll lower it $10!
谢谢…
Grazie…
我能请你喝咖啡吗？
Can I offer you some coffee?
我约会快迟到了
I'm late for an appointment!
这一次不行 也许改天吧！
I can't this time! Ask me another time!
请原谅我现在失陪了
You'll have to excuse me for now.
我希望我能留久一点
I wish I could stay longer!
只要叫我 我就会来的
Just call me and I'll be here!
谢谢你
Grazie.
他不会回来了 他会躲起来的
He won't be back. He'll hide out in the Bronx!
维多 你认为如何？天佑美国
Vito, what do you think?
我们会鸿图大展的
We'll make a big business!
- 纽约市 - 不介意大声点吧？
- New York City. - We'll make a big business!
纽约市
New York City.
- 你是否为维多柯里昂之子 - 是的 我是
- Are you the son of Vito Corleone? - Yes, I am.
他在哪诞生？
Where was he born?
西西里的柯里昂村
Corleone, Sicily.
他是否有时会使用别号
Did he at times use an alias.
就是别人所说的「教父」
that was known in certain circles as Godfather?
教父是他朋友对他的称呼
Godfather is a term used by his friends.
是种内心的感受与对他的尊敬
One of affection and respect.
主席先生！
Mr. Chairman.
我想证实证人的陈词
I would like to verify the witness' statement.
多年来我的选民中 意大利人后裔不断增加
For years many of my constituents have been of Italian descent.
而我蛮了解他们
I've come to know them well.
他们以支持及友谊来荣耀我
They have honoured me with their support and their friendship.
我可以很骄傲的说
I can proudly say.
我的一些要好的朋友中 有不少是美籍意大利人
that some of my very best friends are Italian-Americans.
主席先生 在这个重要时刻 我必须离席
However, Mr. Chairman, unfortunately I have to leave these proceedings.
去参加我的委员会
in order to preside over a very important meeting.
主持一个极重要的会议
of my own committee.
但在我离开之前 我要说明这个
Before I leave, I do want to say this.
这次关于黑手党的听证会 不管怎么样
that these hearings on the Mafia are in no way whatsoever.
都对意大利人是一种侮辱
a slur upon the great Italian people.
因为根据我自己的 经验与知识我可以断定
I can state from my own knowledge and experience.
美国公民中 最忠贞爱国苦干的人
that Italian-Americans are among the most loyal, most law-abiding,
美籍意大利人是其中的一分子
patriotic, hard-working American citizens in this land.
若我们让一粒老鼠屎 坏了一锅粥的话
It would be a shame, Mr. Chairman.
那会是很可惜的 主席先生
if we allowed a few rotten apples to give a bad nameto the whole barrel.
因为由历史上 伟大的哥伦布时代开始
Ecause from the time of Christopher Columbus.
经过了文艺复兴直到目前
to the time of Enrico Fermi.
美籍意大利人一直是我们国家的 前锋与护卫者
Italian-Americans have been pioneers in building and defending our nation.
他们是土地之盐
They are the salt of the earth.
也是这国家的支柱之一
and one of the backbones of this country.
这边
Here,
这边…
Here…
我想大家都同意我们同僚的话
I think we all agree with our esteemed college.
柯里昂先生
Now, Mr. Corleone.
你已经被知会了你的法律权益
you have been advised as to your legal rights.
我们有一位证人的证词
We have testimony.
一位之前的证人
from a previous witness.
奇契先生
one Willi Cicci.
他作证说你是这国家中
He stated hat you are head of.
最有威力的黑手党家族的老大
the most powerful Mafia family in the country.
- 你是吗？- 不 我不是
- Are you? - No, I'm not.
证人指证你要对1947年 纽约市警官的谋杀案
He testified that you are personally responsible.
及与他一起被杀的 威尔斯索拉索
for the murder of a New York police captain in 1947.
负完全的责任
and with him a man named Virgil Sollozzo.
- 你否认吗？- 是的 我否认
- Do you deny this? - Yes, I do.
1950年时你是否策划杀害
Is it true that in the year 1950 you devised the murder.
所谓纽约市五大家族的老大
of the heads of the "Five Families" in New York.
以稳固你独霸的情况
who assume and consolidate your nefarious power?
这完全是假的 先生
It's a complete falsehood.
奎斯特先生
Mr. Questadt.
你是否拥有 拉斯维加斯三间主要旅馆
Is it true you have a controlling interest in three major hotels in Las Vegas?
不 不是真的！
No, it's not true.
我拥有一些那里旅馆的股票
I own some stock in some of the hotels there.
但数量很少
but very little.
我也有IBM 及电话电报公司的部分股票
I also have stock in IBM and IT&T.
柯里昂先生
Mr. Corleone.
你是否控制了纽约州的 赌场及毒品市场
Mr. Corleone do you have any interests or control over gambling or narcotics…
- 或是有那个兴趣 - 不 我没有
- in the state of New York? - No, I do not.
参议员 我的委托人想要…
Senator, my client would like.
在这委员会面前发表一篇声明
to read a statement.
主席先生！
Mr. Chairman.
主席先生！我认为这篇声明
Mr. Chairman, I think this statement is.
以目前来说是完全不合时宜的
totally out of order at this time.
先生 我的委托人 很诚心诚意的
Sir, my client has answered.
回答了这委员会每一个问题
this committee's questions with sincerity.
他虽有权引用
He hasn't taken.
但他并没有用 宪法第五修正案来回避
the Fifth Amendment.
为了公平起见
so this statement.
我们认为这篇声明该被听到
should be heard!
不 我允许柯里昂先生 读出他的声明
No, I'll allow Mr. Corleone to read his statement.
我会把它列入记录
I'll put it in the record.
为了希望澄清我家庭的名声
In the hopes of clearing my family name.
怀着真挚的愿望想给我的孩子
to give my children their.
公平的享受一个美国式的生活
share of the American way of life.
使他们的姓氏和背景 不用背负恶名
without a blemish on their name and background.
我出席这委员会 并尽可能的合作
I have appeared before this committee and given it all my cooperation.
我必须否认我是罪犯 那对我而言是极为不荣誉
I consider it a great personal dishonour to have to deny that I am a criminal.
我希望以下几点列入记录中
I wish to have the following noted for the record:
在第二次世界大战时
That I served my country faithfully.
我忠心及荣耀的 为我的国家服务
in World War Two and was awarded.
我因保卫我国家的行动
the Navy Cross for actions.
而获颁海军十字勋章
in defence of my country.
我从来没有因任何罪名 被捕或定罪
That I have never been arrested or indicted for any crime.
没有任何证据 使我牵连到犯罪阴谋中
That no proof linking me to any criminal conspiracy.
不管是黑手党或是同乡帮
whether it is called Mafia or Cosa Nostra.
或任何你们想加诸于我的 众所皆知的罪名
or any other name has ever been made public.
虽然有权利这么做
I have not taken refuge behind the Fifth Amendment.
但我并未以第五修正案 作护身符
although I may do so.
我向这委员会挑战
I challenge this committee.
请他们提出任何 不利于我的人证或物证
to produce any witness or evidence against me.
若是他们无法提出
and if they do not.
我希望他们以相同情况
I hope they will have the decency.
在大众面前洗清我的名声
to clear my name with the same publicity.
他们现在已完全的 破坏了我的名声
with which they have besmirched it.
柯里昂先生 我确信我们 都留下了深刻的印象
I'm sure we're all quite impressed.
尤其是你对国家的爱
Particularly with your love for our country.
委员会暂停到下周一上午十点
We'll be in recess until 10 a.m. Monday.
那时候本会将提出证人
when we will produce a witness.
以确定今天对你提出的控诉
who'll corroborate the charges against you.
当时候到了 柯里昂先生
And at which time Mr.Corleone.
你非常可能会被证明有罪
you may very well be subject to indictment for perjury.
我提醒你 你必须随传随到 柯里昂先生 休会
I remind you that you're still under subpoena.Adjourned!
十比一 十比一的机会 你说的
Ten-to-one shot, you said.
十比一的机会
Ten-to-one shot.
他会采用第五修正案 而我输了
He would take the Fifth, and I lose.
你听起来像是我的赌马经纪人
You sound like my bookie.
我欠那傢伙一条命
I owe that monkey my life.
你最好是好好睡一觉
Well, just get a good night's sleep.
是 好好的睡
Yeah.
明天是大日子
You've got a big day tomorrow.
给你买了新西装 新衬衫和新领带
I've got you a new suit, new shirt, new tie.
明天我会亲自给你刮胡子
I'll shave you myself in the morning.
在你五千万名美国同胞面前
You'll look respectable for 50 million.
你会看起来很体面
of your fellow Americans.
我的命 我的命在明天之后 就一文不值了
Tomorrow… My life won't be worth a nickel after tomorrow.
得了吧！我看过了 看了19遍了
Come on! I saw this 19 times.
你的家很漂亮 法兰克
You've got a great home here.
你的余生 没人能接近你
for the rest of your life.Nobody gets near you.
你那里都不能去
you're not going anywhere.
那好极了 美极了
That's great. Beautiful.
我做的好交易
Some deal I made.
你会活的像国王 你会是位英雄
You'll live like a king. You'll be a hero.
你在这里会比多数 在外面的人要活的好
You'll live better here than most people outside.
好一个交易
Some deal!
潘坦居利还活着！
Alive. Pentangeli is alive.
他们怎会找上他的？
How did they get their hands on him?
罗斯 是他设计的 麦克
Roth. He engineered it, Michael.
法兰克想和罗萨多兄弟谈条件
When Frankie went to make a deal with the Rosato brothers.
结果他们想杀了他
they tried to kill him.
他以为是你出卖了他
He thought you double-crossed him.
我们在纽约的人说 他已经半死了
Our people with the detectives said he was half dead.
吓得全身僵硬 大声说你出卖了他
scared, and shouted that you'd turned on him.
他们早就控制他了
They already had him on possession.
做假帐 一级谋杀 还有很多罪名
bookmaking, murder one and more.
联邦调查局把他看的很紧
The FBI has him airtight.
留在一个陆军基地里 24小时保护
He's on an army base, 24 hour guards.
我们想接近他是不可能的
We can't get to him.
你使自己犯下五项伪证罪
You've opened yourself to five counts of perjury.
弗雷多呢？他知道什么？
What about Fredo? What does he know?
他说他什么都不知道
He says he doesn't know anything.
我相信他
and I believe him.
罗斯！他这一次耍的够漂亮
Roth, he… played this one beautifully.
我要和弗雷多谈谈
I'm going to talk to Fredo.
我没有什么好说的 麦克
I haven't got a lot to say, Mike.
我们有时间
We have time.
我被蒙在鼓里
I was kept pretty much in the dark.
我晓得的并不多
I didn't know all that much.
现在呢？
What about now?
有没有什么你知道的 可以帮助我？
Is there anything you can help me out with? Anything you can tell me now?
他们掌握了潘坦居利 我只能告诉你这个
They've got Pentangeli.
我并不晓得会是暗杀 麦克
I didn't know it was going to be a hit, Mike.
我对天发誓我不晓得会是暗杀
I swear to God I didn't know.
强尼欧拉跑来找我
Johnny Ola bumped into me.
在比佛利山
in Beverly Hills.
他说 他想谈谈
He said that he wanted to talk.
他说你和罗斯 在合作做宗大买卖
He said that you and Roth were in on a big deal together.
但若我能帮忙 就算我一份
And that there was something in it for me if I could help him out.
他说 他说你在协调上 态度很强硬
He said that you were being tough on the negotiations.
但若他们能有点协助
but if they could get a little help.
能很快的完成这笔买卖
and close the deal fast.
那会对家族有益
it would be good for the family.
你相信他说的鬼话？
And you believed that story?
你相信那个？
You believed that?
他说算我一份
He said there was something in it for me.
- 我自己的！- 我一向都照料你
- on my own! - I've always taken care of you, Fredo.
照料我？
Taken care of me?!
你是我弟弟 你照料我？
You're my kid brother!You take care of me?
你想过那一点吗？
Did you ever think about that?
你曾想过那一点吗？
Did you ever once think about that?
叫弗雷多去办这个
Send Fredo off to do this.
叫弗雷多去办那个
send Fredo off to do that!
让弗雷多打理 某处的无名夜总会
Let Fredo take care of some Mickey Mouse nightclub somewhere.
叫弗雷多去机场接某个人
Let Fredo fetch somebody at the airport!
我是你哥哥 麦克
I'm your older brother.
而我却被你踏在脚下
but was stepped over!
- 那是爸爸的意思 - 但那不是我要的
- It's the way Pop wanted it. - It's not the way I wanted it!
我能处理事情 我够精明
I can handle things, I'm smart!
不像是每个人所说的我很笨
Not like everybody says.
我很精明 我要被尊重
Like dumb. I'm smart and I want respect!
对这件调查 你能告诉我什么吗？
Is there anything you can tell me about this investigation?
任何一点点？
Anything more?
他们所选用的律师奎斯特 是罗斯的人
The senate lawyer, Questadt… He belongs to Roth.
弗雷多
Fredo…
现在你对我什么也不是？
…you're nothing to me now.
你不是哥哥 也不是朋友
Not a brother, not a friend.
我不想知道你及你的所作所为
I don't want to know you, or what you do.
我不想看见你在旅馆中
I don't want to see you at the hotels.
我不想你接近我的房子
I don't want you near my house.
当你要见母亲时 先通知我 好让我避开
When you see our mother, I want to know in advance, so I won't be there.
了解吗？
You understand?
麦克
Mikey.
在家母还活着的时候 我不要他发生任何事
I don't want anything to happen to him while my mother's alive.
这里比球赛的人还要多
There's more people than at a ballgame in here.
威力奇契在那里
Hey, there's Willi Cicci!
请保持秩序
This committee will come to order!
请说你的姓名
State your name, please.
法兰克潘坦居利
Frank Pentangeli.
你的出生地？
Where were you born?
庞特耐格罗 在巴勒摩的外围
Pontenegro, it's outside of Palermo.
你现在住在哪里？
Where do you live now?
我和联邦调查局的人 住在陆军营舍中
I live in an army barracks with the FBI guys.
我们在这终于有一位证人
We have here a witness.
能进一步的作证 指出麦克柯里昂
that will further testify, to Michael Corleone's.
是这犯罪王国的统领
rule of a criminal empire.
控制全国所有的赌博 也许还有别的国家
that controls all gambling.
这位证人与麦克柯里昂之间
This witness has had no buffer.
没有中间人
between himself and Michael Corleone.
他能合作
He can corroborate enough charges.
我们的控诉就有足够的证据
for us to recommend.
让这委员会
a charge of perjury.
能对麦克柯里昂的罪进行诉讼
against Michael Corleone.
- 参议员 - 谢谢你 吉姆
- Senator. - Thank you, Chairman.
潘坦居利先生
Mr. Pentangeli…
Mr. Pentangeli.
你是柯里昂家族的一员吗？
Were you a member of the Corleone family?
你是否为下述人作事？卡波瑞金 彼得克里曼沙
Did you serve under Caporegime, Peter Clemenza,
还有人称教父的维多柯里昂
and under Vito Corleone, also known as the Godfather?
我…我从来不认得教父
I never knew any Godfather.
我有我自己的家族 参议员
I have my own family.
潘坦居利先生 你是…
Mr. Pentangeli, you…
你在驳斥自己的宣誓笔录
You are contradicting.
与你原先所做的 并且签了字的大相矛盾
your own sworn statement.
我再问你一次 先生
I ask you again, sir.
此时此地在这情况下
here and now under oath,
你曾经是以麦克柯里昂 为首的犯罪组织的成员吗？
were you at any time a member of a crime organisation led by Michael Corleone?
我对那点一无所知
I don't know nothing about that!
我和他的父亲 曾在橄榄油事业共事过
I was in the olive oil business with his father.
但那是很久以前了 如此而已
but that was a long time ago.
我们有份你宣誓的笔录
We have a sworn affidavit.
我们有你的宣誓口供
Your sworn affidavit.
指出你奉麦克柯里昂之命 去谋杀人
that you murdered on the orders of Michael Corleone.
你否认那份自白书吗？
Do you deny this confession.
你是否了解 你的否认会有何结果
and do you realise what will happen if you do?
调查局的人答应我个条件
The FBI guys promised me a deal.
所以我假造很多 麦克柯里昂的事
so I made up a lot of stuff about Michael Corleone.
因为那是他们想要的
just to please them.
但…那全是谎言
But it was all lies.
全都是
Everything!
他们不停的说 麦克柯里昂做了这个
They kept saying, "Michael Corleone did this"
麦克柯里昂做了那个
and "Michael Corleone did that".
所以我说 是 当然 有何不可
So I said, "Yeah, sure. Why not?"
柯里昂先生
Mr. Corleone.
你是否能告诉本委员
would you kindly identify.
坐在你左边的那一位是谁？
the gentleman sitting to your left?
我能回答
I can answer that.
他的名字是文森卓潘坦居利
His name is Vincenzo Pentangeli.
他是否和证人有关系
Is he related to the witness?
是 我相信是他的哥哥
He is, I believe, his brother.
他能到前来宣誓吗？
Will he come forward and be sworn?
先生 这个人不了解英文
He doesn't understand English.
他自费来此
He came at his own expense.
在他弟弟有难时伸出援手
to aid his brother.
他没有收到传票 而且他在他自己国家内的名誉
He's not under subpoena, and his reputation in his own country.
是相当受尊重的
is impeccable.
你是说他对这些事一无所知
He knows nothing about this?
据我了解是一无所知
To my knowledge, nothing.
我要弄清楚这里是怎么一回事
I'm going to find out what happened!
现在休会
This committee is now adjourned.
证人可以退席了
The witness is excused.
参议员！
Senator!
这个委员会应该道歉
This committee owes an apology!
这个委员会应该道歉 参议员
This committee owes an apology. Apology, Senator!
- 麦克！打扰一下 - 亲爱的
- Michael, excuse me. - Hello, darling.
孩子们在外面 我们要走了
The children are outside. We're going.
你要去哪？我们要回农场
What do you mean? We're leaving tomorrow.
- 罗可 - 需要我时再叫我
- Rocco? - I'll be in my room, Mike.
麦克 我不回内华达
Michael, I'm not going back to Nevada.
我带孩子们来向你说再见
I brought the children to say goodbye to you.
我要你知道我为你高兴
I'm very happy for you.
我想我一直都知道 你太精明了
I always knew you were too smart.
不会让他们击败你
to let any of them beat you.
- 坐下吧！- 不 我不想久留 不行
- Why don't you sit down? - No, I'm not going to stay long.
有些事我想和你谈谈
There are some things I'd like to talk to you about.
我心理有些事
Things that have been on my mind.
某些我想做的改变
changes I want to make.
我想改变已经太迟了 麦克
I think it's too late for changes, Michael.
我答应我自己不说什么
I wasn't going to say anything…
- 但现在… - 你说太迟是什么意思？
- but now… - What do you mean, "too late"?
潘坦居利究竟发生了何事？麦克
What really happened with Pentangeli?
他哥哥来了
His brother came and helped him.
我不晓得他有哥哥
I didn't even know he had a brother.
他现在在哪里？
Where is he now?
在飞机上 回西西里去了
He's on a plane, back to Sicily.
他只要露个脸就行了
All he had to do was show his face.
那是他们兄弟之间的事 凯
It was between the brothers, Kay.
和我无关
I had nothing to do with it.
没人可以走 你不行 孩子们也不行
Don't tell me you're going, Not you, not the kids.
你听到没？你是我的太太 他们是我的孩子
No, You're my wife and my children.
我爱你 我不允许 就是这样
I love you and won't allow it.
麦克 你说你爱我 然后你又说允许我离去
You say you love me, but talk about allowing me to leave!
男人跟女人之间 总是不断的有事发生
That have been going on for years between mean and women.
那是永远不变的 如此而已
that will not change an that's it.
- 麦克！…你变得盲目了 - 对什么盲目？
- You've become blind! - Blind to what?
看！看我们间发生了什么事？
Look what's happened to us.
麦克！我的天！
Mike!my God,
看看我们的儿子 麦克
Look what's happened to our son, Michael.
- 什么都没有发生 - 别告诉我没发生什么
- Nothing's happened to him. - Don't tell me nothing's…
- 一切都很好 - 一切都不好
- Anthony's fine. - Anthony's not fine!
- 我不想听！- 你要听
- I don't wanna hear about it. - You will hear about it!
- 我不想听！- 没有一件事是好的
- I don't wanna hear about it! - Anthony's friends…
- 我不想听 - 你想骗谁？
- I don't want to hear about it.- are your buttonmen!
我不想听
I don't want to hear about it!
结束了
Over!
在这一刻 我对你毫无爱意
At this moment I feel no love for you at all.
我从没想到那会发生
I never thought that would ever happen.
但发生了
but it has.
凯
Kay…
我们明天走
We're leaving tomorrow.
凯 你为何不带孩子回房去
Why don't you take the kids back to their room?
麦克 你没听到我说的
Michael, you haven't heard me.
凯 你想要我怎么样？
Kay, what do you want from me?
你期望我会让你走？
Do you expect me to let you go.
你期望我会让你 由我身边带走我的孩子？
to let you take my children from me?
你难道不了解我？
Don't you know me?
你难道不晓得那是不可能的
Don't you know that.
那是不可能发生的
that's an impossibility?
你不知道我会尽全力 来阻止那件事发生？
That I'd use all my power to keep that from happening?
你难道不晓得吗？
Don't you know that?
凯
Kay…
在这段时间后
In time.
你会有不同的感受
you'll feel differently.
你会高兴我现在阻止了你
You'll be glad I stopped you now.
我晓得的
I know that.
我知道你因为失去胎儿而怪我
I know you blame me for losing the baby.
我知道那对你有何意义
I know what that meant to you.
我会补偿你的 凯
I'll make it up to you, Kay.
我发誓我会补偿你 我…
I swear I'll make it up to you. I'll…
我会改变
I'm going to change.
我会变的
I'll change.
我知道我有能力改变
I've learned that I have the strength to change.
那么你就能忘了这次小产
Then you'll forget about this miscarriage…
我们再怀一个孩子
…and we'll have another child.
继续生活在一起
And we'll go on, you and I.
你和我白首偕老
We'll go on.
麦克！
Oh, Michael!
麦克！你的眼瞎了！
Michael, you are blind.
那不是小产 那是坠胎
It wasn't a miscarriage.It was an abortion.
坠胎！麦克 就像我们的婚姻一样
An abortion, Michael. Just like our marriage is an abortion.
一件不神圣而且邪恶的事
Something that's unholy and evil!
我不想要你的儿子！麦克
I didn't want your son, Michael!
我不会再生一个你的儿子
I wouldn't bring another one of your sons into this world!
是坠胎！麦克
It was an abortion, Michael.
那是个儿子 儿子 而我杀了他
It was a son and I had it killed.
因为这一切都必须结束
because this must all end!
我知道现在全结束了
I know now that it's over.
我那时就知道了
I knew it then.
没有办法了 麦克
There would be no way, Michael.
你永远不可能原谅我
no way you could ever forgive me.
连这已经延续了二千年的 西西里的传统也不行
Not with this Sicilian thing that's been going on for 2, 000…
- 你不准带走我的孩子 - 我会的
- You won't take my children. - I will.
- 你不准带走我的孩子 - 他们也是我的孩子
- You won't take my children! - They're my children too.
孩子 你在干什么？不要打架
Hey, Sonny.what you doing, don't make a fight.
西西欧
Ciccio.
西西欧阁下
Don Ciccio.
西西欧阁下 是我汤马西诺
Don Ciccio, it's Tommasino.
容我介绍一个人
Allow me the honor of introducing someone.
我在美国纽约的合伙人
My partner in America, in New York.
他的名字是维多柯里昂
His name is Vito Corleone.
我们由这运橄榄油给他
We'll send him olive oil from here.
运到他美国的公司 杰安可橄榄油公司
To his company in America.
他们进口橄榄油 西西欧阁下
They're olive oil importers, Don Ciccio.
西西欧阁下 我们想要得到你的祝福
We'd like your blessing.
及你对我们工作的允许
and your permission to start work.
这位年轻朋友由纽约前来
Where is this young man from New York?
叫他走近一点
Have him come closer.
我看不太清楚
I can't see him so good.
西西欧阁下 我向你致意
My respects, Don Ciccio.
请给我你的祝福
Give me your blessing.
保佑你
Bless you!
你叫什么名字？
What's your name?
我叫维多柯里昂
Vito Corleone.
维多柯里昂
你用了这村子的名字作姓氏
You took the name of this town!
你父亲的名字呢？
And what's your father's name?
他的名字是安东尼奥安东里尼
His name was… Antonio Andolini.
大声点 我的听力不行了
Louder, I don't hear so good.
家父的名字是 安东尼奥安东里尼
My father's name was Antonio Andolini…
而这是给你的
…and this is for you!
麦克！说再见
Michael, say goodbye.
你好 艾尔
Hi, Al.
汤姆 我能与你谈一会吗？
Can I speak with you for a second, Tom?
汤姆 麦克在哪？
Tom, where's Mike?
在等你离开
Waiting for you to leave.
我能与他谈谈吗？
Can I talk with him?
抱歉 弗雷多 没有机会
Sorry, Fredo. No chance.
- 我能见他吗？- 他在会议室
- Can I see him? - He's in the boathouse.
麦克！我是康妮
Michael, it's Connie.
麦克！
Michael.
若是可以的话 我想住在家里
I'd like to stay close to home now, if it's all right.
凯会来吗？
Is Kay coming?
不
No.
麦克 弗雷多在家里陪妈妈
Fredo's in the house with Mama.
他要求见你 汤姆说你不愿见他
He asked for you and Tom said you wouldn't see him.
没错
That's right.
孩子们 你们到外面去一会
Kids, why don't you go outside for a while?
麦克！拜托 我想和你谈谈
Please, I want to talk to you.
麦克！我恨你 那么多年来一直恨你
Michael, I hated you for so many years.
过去我对我自己所做的事 伤害我自己
I think I did things to myself, to hurt myself.
那样你才晓得 我也伤害了你
so that you'd know that I could hurt you.
你只是为了我们大家而坚强就像爸爸以前那样
You were just being strong for all of us, the way Papa was.
我原谅你
And I forgive you.
你不能原谅弗雷多吗？
Can't you forgive Fredo?
他是那么的甜
He's so sweet.
没有你是那么的无助
and helpless without you.
你需要我 麦克
You need me.
我现在想来照顾你
I want to take care of you now.
康妮
Connie…
坐
Tom, sit down.
我们的朋友兼生意伙伴 海门罗斯上报了
Our friend and business partner, Hyman Roth, is in the news.
你知道吗？
Did you hear about it?
我听说他在以色列
I hear that he's in Israel.
以色列的最高法院
The High Court in Israel.
驳回他返回以色列居住的申请
turned down his request to live there.
他的护照过期了 只好回美国来
His passport's been invalidated, except to return here.
他昨天飞到布宜诺斯艾利斯
He landed in Buenos Aires yesterday.
他提议只要他们准许他居留 他愿拿出一百万元
He offered them a million dollars if they'd let him live there.
他们拒绝了他
They turned him down.
上面说他在尝试巴拿马
He's going to try Panama.
巴拿马不会接受他的
Panama won't take him.
一百万或一千万都不行
Not for a million, not for ten million.
他的医疗报告显示他情况很差
His condition is reported as terminal.
反正只能再活六个月
He's only got six months left.
他的心脏病使他濒临死亡 快20年了
He's had the same heart attack for 20 years.
他坐飞机飞往迈阿密
That plane goes to Miami.
没错！我就是要在那儿下手
That's right. That's where I want it met.
麦克 那是不可能的
Impossible.
他们会把他直接交给有关单位
They'll turn him over to the Internal Revenue.
先是海关接着是联邦调查局
Customs and FBI.
不是不可能的
It's not impossible.
没有任何事是不可能的
Nothing's impossible.
那就像想刺杀总统一样
It will be like try to kill the president.
没有接近他的办法
There's no way we can get to him!
汤姆 你令我惊讶
Tom, you surprise me.
若在这生命中有任何确定的事
If anything in this life is certain…
若是历史教了我们任何东西
…if history has taught us anything…
那就是你可以杀任何人
…it's that you can kill anyone.
罗可
Rocco?
困难 但不是不可能的
Difficult. Not impossible.
很好
Good.
若我进来时就有不对劲 你干嘛还问我？
Why did you ask me if something was wrong when I came in?
我想你会告诉我…
I thought you were going to tell me.
你要把你家搬去拉斯维加斯
that you're moving your family to Vegas.
有人请你去当 休斯顿饭店的副总裁
and that you'd been offered the Vice Presidency of the Houstan hotels there.
- 我以为你会告诉我 - 我拒绝了他们
- I thought you'd tell me that. - I turned them down.
我得告诉你 我每次拒绝的事吗？
Must I tell you every offer I turn down?
- 我们谈正事吧！- 好吧
- Let's do business. - All right.
只要考虑一下 麦克 考虑一下
Just consider this, Michael.Just consider it.
罗斯和罗萨多兄弟 本来就在跑路了
Roth and the Rosatos are on the run.
这值得吗？我们够强壮吗？
Are they worth it, are we strong enough?
是否值得？
Is it worth it?
我是说你赢了 你还想要干掉每一个人
You've won. Do you want to wipe everybody out?
我不觉得我需要干掉每一个人 汤姆
I don't feel I have to wipe everybody out, Tom.
只有我的敌人 如此而已
Just my enemies, that's all.
你对我要做的事表示同意 还是另有打算？
Are you with me in these things, or what?
因为若不同意的话
Because if not.
你可以带着你太太 你的家人
you can take your wife, your family.
及你的情妇
and your mistress.
全部搬到拉斯维加斯去
and move them all to Las Vegas.
你为何要伤害我？麦克
Why do you hurt me, Michael?
我一向对你忠心
I've always been loyal to you.
我是说…这是怎么一回事？
What is this?
所以…你留下来？
So… you're staying?
- 是 我留下 - 好
- Yes, I'm staying. - Okay.
现在 你要我做的是什么事？
What do you want me to do?
安东尼
Anthony.
安东尼 你想不想…
Hey, Anthony…
我教你如何抓真正的大鱼 如何？
How would you like it if I taught you how to catch the really big fish?
- 你想学吗？- 好
- Would you like that? - Okay.
你知道我在你这个年纪时
You know, when I was your age…
我和我所有的兄弟一起去钓鱼
…I went out fishing with all my brothers.
还有我父亲 大家一起
and my father. Everybody.
而我是唯一钓到鱼的
I was the only one that caught a fish.
除了我没有人钓到了
Nobody else could catch one.
你知道我怎么做到的？
Do you know how I did it?
每一次我把钓线丢入水中时
Every time I put the line in the water.
我说圣母玛丽亚
I said a Hail Mary.
每次我说圣母玛丽亚 我都钓到鱼
and every time I said a Hail Mary, I caught a fish.
你相信吗？
Do you believe that?
是真的 那是个秘密
It's true. That's the secret.
我们到湖上时 你想试试吗？
Do you want to try it out on the lake?
- 好 - 好
- Okay.- Okay.
你还带了什么？
What else have you got?
不会有事的 法兰克 别担心
Everything will be okay.
我哥哥回去了吗？
Did my brother go back?
走了 别担心
Yeah, don't worry.
他比我凶悍十倍
He's ten times tougher than me, my brother.
他是旧式的人
He's old-fashioned.
他连出去吃晚饭都不肯
He didn't want dinner.
他只想直接回家
just wanted to go home.
那就是我哥哥
That's my brother!
没有任何事能让他离开那小镇
Nothing could get him away from that two-mule town.
他可以在这称王的 他可以拥有自己的家族
He could have been big here. He could have had his own family.
汤姆 我现在该怎么做？
Tom, what do I do now?
法兰克
Frankie.
你一向对政治及历史有兴趣
You were always interested in politics and history.
我记得你提到1933年的希特勒
I remember you talking about Hitler back in '33.
我仍然读很多书 我在里面学到不少好东西
Yeah, I still read a lot. I get good stuff in there.
你是老前辈身旁的人
You were around the old-timers.
他们梦想着应该如何组织家族
who built the organisation of the families.
他们如何以古罗马军团为基础
basing them on the old Roman legions.
还给他们命名为统治者 议事者和军士
with "regimes", "capos" and "soldiers".
还真的成功了
And it worked.
是 它成功了
Yeah, it worked.
那是伟大的老日子 你知道吗？
Those were the great old days, you know.
我们就像是罗马帝国
We was like the Roman Empire.
柯里昂家族就像是罗马帝国
The Corleone family was like the Roman Empire.
它曾经有一度是
Yeah, it was once.
法兰克
Frankie.
一旦对抗帝国的长老失败了
When a plot against the Emperor failed…
阴谋者总是保有一次机会
…the plotters were always given a chance…
好让家族保有财富 对不对？
…to let their families keep their fortunes. Right?
是 但那只是有钱人 汤姆
Only the rich guys.
小人物呢？他们被打倒
The little guys got knocked off.
而他所拥有的悉数归于帝国
and all their estates went to the Emperors.
除非他们回家自杀
Unless they went home and killed themselves.
那就不会发生任何事
then nothing happened.
而他的家庭
And their families.
他的家庭会被妥善照顾 汤姆
were taken care of.Tom.
那是个好的机会 好交易
That was a good break, a nice deal.
他们回到家里
They went home…
坐在装满热水的浴缸里
and sat in a hot bath.
把血管割开 流血至死
opened up their veins and bled to death.
有时候他们在自尽之前 还会有个派对
And sometimes they had a little party before they did it.
别担心任何事 法兰克长老
Don't worry about anything, Frankie Five-Angels.
谢了 汤姆 谢了
Thanks, Tom. Thanks.
再见了 汤姆
See you, Tom.
再见了 法兰克
Addio, Frankie.
凯 你必须走了
Kay… You have to go.
你那么的漂亮
So pretty.
凯 请快点 他来了
Kay, please hurry. He's coming.
安东尼 和妈妈吻别
Anthony… Kiss Mama goodbye.
安东尼 去和你妈吻别 行吗？
Anthony, would you kiss your mother good bye.
安东尼 向妈妈说再见 安东尼
Anthony, say good bye to mama, Anthony.
我爱你 宝贝
honey I love you.
凯！拜托！
Kay, please.
好吧！…
All right.
玛莉 到这来
Mary, come here.
安东尼 请你再吻我一次
Anthony, please. Kiss me once.
小心 接稳了
Easy.
安东尼…
Anthony! Anthony!
他在这 我们要去钓鱼
He's here we're going fishing!
不 麦克现在要带他去雷诺
No.Michael want to take him to Reno now.
可恶
Shit!
好了 孩子 你得和你爸爸去雷诺
Okay, kid, you have to go to Reno with your pop.
安东尼 别这样 我明天再带你去钓鱼
I'll take you fishing tomorrow.
- 好吗？- 好
- Okay? - Okay.
好了
That a boy.
安东尼 我用那秘密为你钓一条鱼回来
Hey, Anthony, Listen, I'll catch one for you in secret.
- 好吗？- 好
- Okay? - Okay.
去吧
Let's go.
艾尔 我们走
Al let's go.
罗斯先生 你了解我必须把你收押
Mr. Roth, I must take you into custody.
是的 我了解
I understand.
你能对以色列最高法院作出的裁决
What's your reaction to.
说一下你的反应吗？
the Israeli High Court ruling?
我是个领养老金的退休投资者
I'm a retired investor on a pension.
我去以色列是因为 在我的风烛残年
I went to Israel to live there as a Jew.
我想以一个犹太人的 身份住在那
in the twilight of my life.
法兰克 出来吧！我们来玩牌
Hey, Frankie! Come on out, let's play some Hearts.
法兰克
Frankie!
罗斯先生 你的身家真的超过三亿美金？
Is it true you're worth over 300 million dollars?
我是退休的投资者 靠养老金过活
I'm a retired investor, living on a pension.
我回来是参加总统大选投票
I came home to vote in the presidential election.
因为他们不给我 一张缺席的选举票
because they wouldn't give me an absentee ballot.
站住！
Halt!
老天爷！
Jesus Christ.
圣母玛丽亚 祈求你的保佑
Hail Mary, full of grace.
主与我同在
The Lord is with thee.
赐福予妇女
Blessed art thou amongst women.
赐福予你所孕育的果实
Blessed is the fruit of thy womb, Jesus.
圣母玛丽亚！上帝之母 为我们这群罪人祈祷吧
Holy Mary, Mother of God, pray for us sinners.
每一个人 注意
Hey! Everybody, pay attention.
这是我朋友卡洛李兹
This is my friend Carlo Rizzi.
这是我弟弟弗雷多 你认识他
You know my brother Fredo.
- 当然 我认识他 - 这是我的养兄汤姆
- Sure. - This is my stepbrother Tom.
那是他的女友泰瑞莎
and that's his girl Theresa.
这里这个可人儿是我妹妹康妮
This cute little thing is my sister Connie.
我向你提起过的
I told you about that.
来吧！向卡洛打招呼
Say hello to Carlo.
- 他很帅 对吧？- 是的
- He's good-looking? - Yes.
那个无精打采的傢伙 是我弟弟麦克
The droopy thing is Mike.
我们叫他大学生 知道我的意思吧
We call him Joe College.
- 来吧 坐吧 彼此谈谈 - 坐吧
- Sit down. Talk to each other. - Sit down.
爱因斯坦先生…
Hey, Mr. Einstein…
- 蛋糕在这 - 泰西欧来了
- The cake. - Sally, get in here!
- 我很害怕 - 来吧！
- I was scared. - Come on.
令尊在哪？
Where's your father?
- 他去做圣诞节采购快回来了 - 放在这
- Christmas shopping. - Put here.
让我们看看
Let's see that thing.
漂亮吧？
That's nice!
- 我应该现在插蜡烛吗？- 插吧！
- Should I put the candles on now? - Yea go on.
- 卡洛 你帮她好不好？- 当然
- Yeah. You help her, Carlo. - Sure.
你好 泰西欧
Hello, Tessio.
那是什么？兰姆酒吗？
What is that? Rum?
他们说是
Yeah.
别偷吃菜 爸回来前别碰菜
Hey Sonny, don't touch the ante-pasta until Pop gets here.
好了
Yea, come on.
你们说日本人的胆量如何？
What do you think of the nerve of those Japs?
想修理那些混蛋吧？
those slanty eyed bastards, huh.
还在爸爸生日的这一天 在后院扔炸弹
Dropping bombs in out back yard and on Pops birthday ya know.
- 他们并不晓得是爸爸生日 - 他们并不晓得是爸爸生日
- Now they didn't know it was Pop's birthday. - They didn't know it was Pop's birthday.
在石油禁运之后 我们就该料到的
Not surprising after the oil embargo.
料想到有什么用 不管料到料不到扔炸弹
What do you mean expect it,
他们都没有扔炸弹的权利
expect it or not they have no right dropping bombs.
你是什么？亲日分子？站错边了
What are you a Jap lover or something are you on their side?
我知道今早有三万人志愿从军
I understand 30, 000 enlisted this morning.
一群笨蛋
Bunch of saps.
他们为什么是笨蛋？
Why are they saps?
尚尼 别这样 我们不必谈论战争
Sonny, come on.We don't have to talk about the war.
宝贝 你去和卡洛聊天 好不好？
Hey beat it, you go talk to Carlo alright.
他们是笨蛋
They're saps.
因他们为陌生人冒生命危险
because they risk their lives for strangers.
那是爸爸的语气
Now that's Pop talking…
一点也没错 那是爸爸的语气
You're god damn right that's Pop talking.
他们为国家冒生命危险
They risk their lives for their country.
这国家不是你的血脉 你要记住
Country isn't your blood, you remember that.
我不觉得是那样
I don't feel that way.
你不觉得是那样
Well if you don't fell that way.
你若不觉得是那样 你为何不休学去从军呢？
why don't you just quit collage and go to…go to join the Army.
我那么做了 我加入了海军
I did.I've enlisted in the Marines.
麦克 你为何不先来找我们？
Why didn't you come to us?
此话怎讲？
What do you mean?
我是说爸爸花了很大的力量
I mean Pop had to pull a lot of strings.
- 才让你缓徵的 - 我没那么要求
- to get you a deferment. - I didn't ask for it.
我没要求缓徵 我并不想要
and I didn't want it.
- 你是怎么一回事 - 别这样！…别打了
- What's wrong? - Come on! Knock it off!
- 尚尼 - 混蛋
- Sonny - Punk!
- 尚尼！坐下 - 坐！坐下
- Sonny, sit down. - Sit down.
妈！爸又在打架了！
Mommy, Daddy's fighting again!
你带卡洛到客厅去
Go and show Carlo the tree.
麦克叔叔 妈妈 爸爸
Uncle Miclael, mama, pop.
老天爷 你真行 在爸爸的生日上伤他的心
Nice, real nice, break your fathers heart on his birthday.
做的好 麦克 恭喜你
That's swell, Mike. Congratulations.
没错 鼓励他
Go on encourage him.
去 倒杯酒给我 去吧
I want…I want you to get me a drink, go on.
你不了解 你父亲对你有计划的
Now you don't understand but, uh, your father has big plans for you.
很多次他都提到了你的未来
Now many times he and I have talked about your future.
- 你和我父亲谈我的未来？- 是的
- Talked to my father about my future? - Yes.
我的未来？
My future?
麦克 他对你期望很高
Mikey, he has high hopes for you.
我对我的未来有我自己的计划
Well I have my own plans for my future.
你上大学是去变笨的吗？你真的笨了
What'd you go to collage to get stupid? You're really stupid.
他回来了 快点
He's here come on.
来吧！…
Come on…
笨蛋！
Stupid!
大惊喜！
Surprise!